<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise against the folishnesse of men in differinge the reformation of their liuing and amendment of their manners, compyled by the godly lerned man John Riuius, and translated into Englishe by Iohn Bankes.</title>
            <title>De stultitia mortalium, in procrastinanda correctione vitæ. English</title>
            <author>Rivius, Johann, 1500-1553.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise against the folishnesse of men in differinge the reformation of their liuing and amendment of their manners, compyled by the godly lerned man John Riuius, and translated into Englishe by Iohn Bankes.</title>
                  <title>De stultitia mortalium, in procrastinanda correctione vitæ. English</title>
                  <author>Rivius, Johann, 1500-1553.</author>
                  <author>Bankes, John, fl. 1550.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[216] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the signe of the George next to Saynte Dunstones churche by Wyllyam Powell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: De stultitia mortalium, in procrastinanda correctione vitæ.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>ornamental border containing device of William Middleton (McKerrow 106)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ A TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST</hi> the foliſhneſſe of men in differringe the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their liuing, and amendment of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Compyled by the godly lerned man Iohn Riuius, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſhe by Iohn Bankes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:2"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE MOSTE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and his ſingular good lorde, the lorde Marques Dorſette his lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, his humble oratour Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth grace and helthe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I weye with my ſelfe, &amp; diligently examine the ſimilitude in S. Paul where he compareth the Churche of Chriſt to a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (moſte honorable Lorde) I fynde that he can not iuſtely be taken for a membre of the ſame, which doth not imploy his ſtudies to this ende, that he may likewiſe conferre ſome thing therunto in his vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and calling, as in the naturall body euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre helpeth the whole: For we ſe, that there is in a naturall body ſuche an affection, and deſyre of euerye mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre to helpe and maynteyne thother, that not onely the ſenſes be redye to do their part and office, as the eye to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:3"/> ſee, the eare to here, and ſo likewyſe in the teſte of the ſenſes, but alſo all the other partes of the bodye do ſoo muche care for the whole, that they ſhunne no danger, thoughe it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great, to helpe and ſuccour the ſame. If any man than, which bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the name of a chriſtian, ſhal ſpy for the any thyng, that may conduce and profyte the miſticall bodye, and dothe not his endeuour to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte to brynge the ſame thervnto: verely he is to be thought an vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable membre, not worthye in my iudgemente to be accompted of that membre, of whom Chriſt is the head. Surely it myghte be a great ſhame for vs Chriſtians, if we ſhoulde not (hauyng ſuch light of the goſpel, as we haue) endeuour in ſome wyſe to profite the common welth of Chriſt, when we ſhal call to mynde the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaienge of the moſte diuine phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:3"/> whiche is, that we be not borne for our ſelues onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but parte of our birth our natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey doth chalenge vnto it, part our parentes, and an other parte alſo our family<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and frendes. Plato dyd knowe onely by the lyghte of naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, that al excellent and good gyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes came of god, and were gyuen to thintent that a man ſhulde therwith helpe, and profyte others. Of the whiche opinion were alſo al the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, whiche had taſted of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt diſcipline and learnynge.</p>
            <p>Who ſo euer therfore doth thincke hym ſelfe to be a membre of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth of Chriſte, whiche is his myſtycall body, he muſt nedes much more be enforced of Chriſtian know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and charitie to imploy his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in beſtowing thoſe giftes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god hath gyuen him, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte of others. Nowe than ſeynge
<pb facs="tcp:4762:4"/> that among the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of this ſame miſticall body many of theim be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with greuous diſeaſes, as deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peracyon, to much affyance in them ſelues, and truſt in theyr owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and other groſſe erroures, as ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſticion, idolatrie. &amp;c. wherby the moſt iuſt wrath, and indygnation of god is prouoked agaynſte them, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye he were verye vnnaturall, and ſhulde t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtifie that he had not taſted of the ſpirite of god, which neyther moued with thexample of the hethen nor with loue towardes the brethren conſyderynge the greate daungers, that myght enſue here vpon, wolde take ſome paynes, and endeuoure to procure medicines, ſo farre forth as in him lieth to eaſe, and helpe the ſame. We haue exaumples hereof, wherwith we might be much moued continued by the moſt gratious wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng of god, euen from the apoſtels
<pb facs="tcp:4762:4"/> tyme. For the holy fathers, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres beſyde theyr greate trauayle in confutynge of hereſies (whiche was, and myght be a ſufficient teſtimonie of theyr zele, and diligence) haue left alſo ſondrye monumentes, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes aſwell parteynynge to the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of mens maners and behauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as alſo to the confirmynge of their conſciences. And not only they but alſo men of this our age: for what godly wyttes hath god ſtirred vp? And howe diligently haue they applyed theyr ſtudyes, and beſtowed theyr talentes in garniſhynge good learnyng, and ſettyng forth the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and pure worde of god? and to paſſe ouer them, that haue taken ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng great paynes in foreine, and ſtraung countries, euen here in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, god hath moued many with ſondry gyftes, ſome to be able to ſet forthe workes of theyr owne, and to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:5"/> hunte the Romyſhe fox, and ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with open mouth to crye out agaynſt hym, &amp; other ſome to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of other mennes. &amp;c. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto hath god alſo reiſed vp the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of noble men, that they doo not onely aſſiſt, and defende them, that beſtowe their laboure herein, but alſo helpe forwarde with the ſame them ſelues: amonge whom I may moſte worthely recompt your lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, whiche hath ben euer enclined to the ſettynge forthe of true godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and religion, and to the rotyng out of falſe and fey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed ſuperſticion. whervnto god hath alſo prouyded for you alwayes miniſters for the ſame. I therfore (though my talent be but ſmale) moued with theſe, and ſuch lyke examples, thought that I coulde not be iuſtly rekened or take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a membre of the miſtical body of Chriſte, if that, when all true chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb facs="tcp:4762:5"/> be ſo buſily occupied, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo dilgently in the lordes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, I ſhoulde be founde ydle, and vnoccupied, like to the ſeruaunte in the goſpell, whiche hyd his talente, and brought it not forthe to profyte others. This laſt wynter therfore, whan I redde ouer two lytle bokes, whiche D. Iohn Riuius an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lerned, and godlye man, compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the latyne tongue, thone of the refourmacion of mans maners, and lyuynge, the other of encouragynge them to dye, that be vexed with ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and marueylynge muche, that ſuch two bokes coulde be kepte hyd ſo long, and not tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe, conteynynge ſuche a profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and neceſſarie matter, ſo apt and conuenient for our time: I thought that I ſhuld not be euyl occupied if I tranſlated the ſame in to Engliſhe that they might be made commune,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:6"/> and profite the more, which whan I had finiſhed, muſynge with my ſelfe vnto what patrone I mought beſte directe the ſame. I founde none lyke to your lordſhyp, whether your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfolde vertues or your zele to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the glory of god be conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And verely it ſemed to me, that it could not honeſtly be dewe to any beſydes your lordſhyp, for ſo muche as it was done in your lordſhyppes houſe. The one parte of my labour which is now finiſhed, I bryng, and humbly preſent to your lordſhyp at this time, not bycauſe you haue any nede her of for your ſelf, but bycauſe if it ſhoulde be commended by your lordeſhip, it myght be the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, and profite the more. For be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides thopinion that men haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of other vertues, where with your lordeſhyp is endued, they haue alſo conceiued a ſinguler opinion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4762:6"/> the zele your lordſhyppe hath to ſet forth the pure worde of god, and to rote out falſe and feined ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which thing may apere very plaine, (as they alſo gather) bothe by other thynges, and alſo by thorder taken in your lordeſhyppes houſe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the true worſhypyng, and due ſeruynge of god. wherfore ſeynge that the thynge of it ſelfe is ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and neceſſary, vndoubtedly it can not be but very wel receyued of all men, if your lordſhyps commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion be there vnto added, whiche thynge if it come to paſſe, I doubte not, but as it hath profyted much in the latine tongue, ſo ſhal it ſumwhat alſo do good in Englyſhe. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it is not ſo finely tranſlated yet I truſt that the mynde of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore is ſo expreſſed that mine indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrye and labour herein, can not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be reprehended, and fault founde
<pb facs="tcp:4762:7"/> withall of the tentyll and fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reder, whom I ſhal in this place moſte hartely require for to accepte this my doynge, and interprete eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thynge herein, as he ought to do, for ſo muche as this is euen the firſt fruites of my wyt: and in ſo doynge (if I ſhall perceyue that this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure ſhall profyte the ſame) I ſhall be muche encouraged to go forward in ſuche lyke ſtudyes, as may moſte conduce, and hereafter to enterpriſe greater thynges. But fearyng leſte I haue ben to tediouſe to your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, and deteyned you longer, than becommeth me to do, from the ſwete and comfortable readynge of Riui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. I commytte the boke into your lordeſhyppes handes, beſechyng the euerlaſtynge and immortal God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lorde, and redemer Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, that he wyl graunt you dayely, more and more encreaſe of
<pb facs="tcp:4762:7"/> knowledge in his truthe, and kepe your hart awake contynually to glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifie hym, that by thexample of your lordſhyp others maye be ſtyred vp vnto godlye lyuynge: and that he wyll aſſiſt you, and further you in al your godly affaires, which with the ſonne, and holye ghoſt reygneth for euer: to whome be gyuen all prayſe, honour, and glorye. So be it,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your lordeſhyppe his humble oratour Iohn Bankes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:8"/>
            <head>¶ A TREATISE AGAINST the foliſhenes of men, in differrynge the reformation of theyr lyuyng, and amendment of theyr maners.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F SVCHE men, as wyll be taken for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians wold flee and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte ſo muche the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Epicures, &amp; Saduceis, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to deteſt the name, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theim, verely they wolde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine, and temper them ſelues from wyckednes and miſchiefe, and wold vſe and exerciſe vertuous and godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyuyng, no leſſe than they nowe lyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſtinately in vice, and behaue them ſelues in al theyr doynges both wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly, &amp; vngodly. And agayne the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wolde none otherwyſe obſerue, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kepe the commaundementes of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> myghty god, than they now neythe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feare hym, nor dread him at al. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4762:8"/> vndoubtedlye, there is not one al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, whiche dothe ſo much abhorre the thynge it ſelfe in his herte (which thyng may playnely appeare by our dayely conuerſacion, our maners, and al that euer we do) as we eſchew and flee the name. For how can thoſe men be aſſured, in theyr conſcience, that ſoules are immortall, which for the moſt parte lyue, as brute beaſtes do. Or that there be rewardes repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the godlye in heauen, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ordeyned for wycked men in hell, which do in no maner thyng feare to tranſgreſſe, and breake the commaundemente of god? and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fal headlong into all kynde of vyce, and enormities, as though they dyd imagine, that eyther god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng ſtocke, and a feined thynge, or the ſowles and bodyes do dye bothe at once? And to graunt, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be ſome men, which do both feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4762:9"/> and doubt not, but that he wyl both rewarde, and alſo punyſhe euery one acordyngly, as he hath deſerued (of the which ſort there be but very few) Nowe I beſeche you, what man is there, whom eyther the feare of gods iuſtice doth withdrawe from vice, or yet doth induce, and bryng in minde to refourme, and amende his lyfe? wherin thou mayeſt iuſtly lamente, and bewaile the folly and ſtate of vs al, and much wonder at our blynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or rather madnes, which in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhortnes, and vncertenty of lyfe doo ſo behaue our ſelues, that we haue no mynde of any reformacion, or amendment of our lyfe, when we be croked for old age, and haue than ſkarſly one daye to lyue: ſo farre of is it, that we go aboute, or entende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that thynge, whan we be yonkers, and in our floryſhyng age. When I remembre with my ſelfe, that ſuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4762:9"/> is the folly of men, or madnes rather as I may well call it, in deferrynge the reformation of theyr lyfe:</p>
               <p>I thynke it meete, and neceſſarie to ſearch the cauſes out, why we are ſo ſlowe in that weyghtie thynge, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon our ſaluacion doth wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende: for when we ſhal haue ſought forth the cauſes, and declared what they be, I doubt not, but that it ſhal be eaſye for vs to fynde alſo ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for the diſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="causes">
               <div n="1" type="cause">
                  <head>¶ The firſt and principal cauſe.</head>
                  <p>I Thinke therefore that our vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe is the chefeſt and principall cauſe herof. For if we ſuppoſed not, that thoſe thinges were fables, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are mencioned in ſcripture euery where of the laſte dowme, and of the voyce of the Archangell, and of the trumpe of god, and of the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4762:10"/> ſeeate of the Lorde, wherat all men muſt ſtande of the punyſhmente of the wycked, of the euerlaſtynge and bleſſed lyfe, whiche the godlye after this miſerable lyfe ſhall enioye, of the reſurrection of the bodyes, and ſoules, eyther to be partakers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of certayne ioye, or elles of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne peyne, without al queſtion we wolde not lyue thus as we do, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>fferre the reformacion of our lyfe, but wold lyue farre other wyſe, and after an other ſorte, than we do: for what myſlyuer wold not quake both body &amp; ſoule, whan ſo euer he ſhulde remembre the laſt dowme, ſyth that he ſhal in the ſame make a reckening of all thynges, which he hath eyther entended, thoughte, ſayde, or done, and there ſhall ſpeake his owne mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter without any aſſiſtaunte, or man of lawe. Oh terrible iudgement to the wycked, which ſhulde neuer fall
<pb facs="tcp:4762:10"/> out of theyr remembraunce: for ſyth that the iuſt, and godly ſhall vnneth be able to ſtande in this iudgement, where ſhal than the wycked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly appeare? In this iudgement the ſonne of god ſhall ſytte vpon all ſortes of men, beynge than an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryght, ſeuere, ſtreyghte, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable iudge, which is nowe our mediatour, and aduocate with his father. Al kynd of men ſhalbe called vnto a rekening, how they haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed ouer theyr dayes here in yearth. The ſecretes of hertes ſhalbe diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſhewed abrode. The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie of euery mannes conſcience ſhall gyue agaynſt hym ſelfe: ſhall accuſe &amp; condempne hym. And to be ſhorte, god wil punyſhe the vngodly by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt ſeueritie, and moſt fatherly, and mercifully preſerue, and ſaue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocent; that is: as Paul doth inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rete it: god wyll render, and gyue
<pb facs="tcp:4762:11"/> to euery man acordingly, as he hath deſerued. But in this iudgement, not onely the outwarde acte ſhall be condempned: As adultry, fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whordome, wytchcrafte, murder, ſklander, thefte, robbery, ſacrilegie, banketynge, riotinge, drunkennes, vſury, and other ſuch lyke, as bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and vnhoneſte talkynge, fonde, folyſhe, and raſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anglyng without meaſure, liynge, ydle wordes, viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous communicacion, and infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame ſorte, wherwith ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer godlye eares are offended, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alſo the vnſene, and hyd ententes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the herte: ſuch thinges, as we hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wyckedly eyther wyſhed or thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moreouer the naughty affections o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the mynde, which be contrary to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worde of god, as anger, grudge, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred, ennimitie, malyce, enuy, pryd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> couetouſnes, &amp; deſyre of other men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> goodes. &amp;c. Who wold not than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:11"/> remembraunce of this iudgemente withdrawe from vice, and ſtay, leſte he ſhulde fall all together, whiche is perſwaded aſſuredly, that it ſhalbe. One of the olde wryters hath a very good and notable ſayeng. whether I eate or drynke (ſayeth he) or what thyng ſo euer I do, the terible voyce of the archangell ſowneth in myne eares. Ariſe you dead men, come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your dowme: whiche whan I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre, I quake bothe bodye and ſoule. Yf the fleſhe then ſtirreth vp any man vnto beaſtly luſtes, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely pleaſures, or vnto gluttony, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urfettynge, or vnto any ſuch vyce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et hym by and by call to his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce the dreadful day of dowme. Yf proſperitie (as it doth very often) cauſe a man to be hauty and proude, if ryches make a man fearſe, and his mynded: yf honoure, promocion, or high dignitie cauſe a man to think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:12"/> much of hym ſelfe, and to deſpiſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, let hym ſtreyght way remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre the iudgement ſeate of the lorde. Yf anger prycketh any manne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge his quarell: yf grudge, and malyce trouble the hertes of any: yf couetouſnes enforceth a man to rob and deceyue others: yf the worlde doth prouoke any man vnto amby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, pryde, or ryote: yf the deuyl by his ſuttyll, and falſe meanes, and crafte dryue any man to ſpeake blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie agaynſt god, or vnto any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuche myſchefe, let hym thynke none other, but that he ſhal appeare before the iugement ſeate of the lord and ſhall there pleade for hym ſelfe. Let hym feare the ſentence, that the iudge ſhall pronounce, which dothe condempne the wycked to hell fyre. wolde god: wolde god I ſaye, that this day of dowme wolde neuer fall out of mens myndes, Than ſurely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:12"/> euery man wold do, as he ſhulde do. Kinges and rulers wold haue their onely, and ſpecyall care vppon the weal of the communaltie committed to theyr charge, and wolde defende theyr Lybertye, and vpholde, and maynteyne bothe theyr priuate, and publique ordynaunces, and lawes. Of the other part the comons wold ſhew them ſelues loyall &amp; obedient, towarde their liege and ſoueraygne head, and kyng, and wolde not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne to haue him rular ouer them, nor refuſe to pai their rentes towles or trybutes: but otherwyſe wolde render vnto hym aſwell due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and feare, as alſo honour. &amp;c. Euery man wolde loue his wyfe, as his owne ſelfe: the wyues wolde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence theyr huſbandes, and be in ſubiection vnto them, as vnto their lordes and heades. Parentes wold trade, and brynge vp theyr chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:4762:13"/> in godly education, and diſcipline, and as Paule wylleth in the feare &amp; knowledge of god: Agayne chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wolde be obediente towardes theyr parentes in the lord, and wold erneſtly folowe theyr wayes, and bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſely do theyr commandement. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes wold be redy at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of them, which as appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto the fleſh are their maſters and that with all honeſt reuerence, and godly feare, and ſymplicitie of hert: as alſo Paule exorteth. Againe mayſters wolde be meke, and gentil towardes theyr ſeruauntes, beynge well aſſured, that they haue alſo a mayſter in heauen. Paſtoures and myniſters wolde attende the lordes flocke, as they are bounden. Ryche menne wolde relieue the poore with theyr goodes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wydowes wolde pray nyght and day, without ceaſſynge. Poore men wolde take paciently, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4762:13"/> well in worthe theyr pouertie, ſythe that it is the wyl of god, that it ſhal ſo be. The maryed man wolde lyue, as though he had no wyfe. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried man wolde referre al that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he doth vnto the glory of god: what wyl ye more? euery man wold do his offyce and duetie in his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, as he oughte to do: if the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the laſte dowme were euer before his eyes, when god wyll requyre a reckenyng of our whole ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge, and of all our doynges, and wyl gyue to euery man accordingly, as he hath deſerued, eyther rewarde or punyſhment. We ſee dayly with our eyes in a gret and feruent plage tyme, when death is euery houre pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent before mens eyes: howe careful they are, and howe diligentely they go aboute the reformation of their life: ſpecially if they be not ſuche as do vſurpe falſly the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:14"/> What? Ought not we than muche more to go about the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion of our lyfe, at all tymes, all houres, and euerye moment of the houre, and to repent vnfeinedly, and bewayle our wicked and ſynful life, and pacifie the wrath and indignati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of god agaynſt ſynne, ſythe that by caſualitie, and vncertayne chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces death is imminent and at hande euerye houre? A wyſe man therfore wyll ſo leade his lyfe alway, as men vſe commonlye in the daungerous plage time, when they are, as it wer awaked out of theyr dreame, and be carefull, and go erneſtely about the reformacion of theyr lyfe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to chaunge it into better, and to eſchewe vyce, exercyſe iuſtyce and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitte, and finally to pacifie gods wrath, whiche is worthely ſtered, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte vs for our ſynne, by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and remorſe of conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:14"/> I praye you, ought not euery man, when there is no ſuch daunger, nor feare of any plage, to be the like that afore in the hotte and daungerous plage tyme he determined to be? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man wil graunt that the houre of deathe is vncertayne, and that it is a thyng moſt certayn that we ſhal dye, what a great folly is it than to feare death ſo much, which is euery houre at hande: nor to thinke at any tyme of the reformacion of our lyfe? but thus it is. We fele, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the moſt iuſte wrath of god a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aynſt ſyn in aduerſitie, as in plage, famine, yearthquake, daungerous diſſaſes of the body, but in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, when we haue the world at wyl, we feare nat to abuſe the goodnes of god. In this ſtate we remembre nat death, which is iminent euery houre nor the laſte dowme, nor the terrible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hangel, of the which
<pb facs="tcp:4762:15"/> S. Paul maketh mention vnto the Theſſalon.) nor the ſowne of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des trumpe, nor hell, or euerlaſtinge peyne, nor the vnquenchable fyre, nor the darkenes where there ſhalbe wepynge, and gnaſſhynge of teeth. Whiche thynges verely we oughte to remembre at all tymes, whether it be in the mornyng at our vpriſynge, or at night when we go to reſt, or at dynner, or ſupper, or when we bathe our ſelfe for our healthes ſake, or do any ſerious and weighty buſines, or fynally when we refreſhe and recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate our myndes with ſome honeſt pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyme. But the vngodly can not be perſwaded none other, but that theſe thynges are fables, whiche the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſetteth forthe of the laſt dowme, of the iudgement ſeate of the lorde, of the voyce of tharchaungel, of the trumpe of god, of hell, and of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torment and peyne. And like
<pb facs="tcp:4762:15"/> as the heathen in times paſt were per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded, that theſe thynges were fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whiche the poetes feyned of Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tarus and Phlegethon, of Minoe &amp; Radamanthis, of hell, and the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the deueliſhe, and of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame: wherupon Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca toke occaſion to ſaye, that the poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes deluded and feared vs with vain menaſſes and feares: So verayly a great parte of men thynke, that theſe are but tales, and contemne them as vayne thretenynges, whiche are ſette forthe to vs in holy ſcripture, of hell, of eternall death, of the fyre, wherin ſhall be waylynge and gnaſhynge of tethe, of the reſurrection of the ſowle and body together, to partake eyther ioy or peyne, when otherwiſe all theſe thynges do imprynte in the hartes of godly men, and ſuche as lyue in the feare of the lorde, a wonderfull feare and horrour. And are (as the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te
<pb facs="tcp:4762:16"/> ſayth) names, which euen ſowne fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in our eares. Thou haſt the firſt and chefeſt cauſe, why we for the moſt parte all of vs in this wyſe differ the reformacion of our lyfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="cause">
                  <head>¶ The ſeconde cauſe.</head>
                  <p>NOwe let vs procede vnto an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, which is the hope of the mercy of god: this hope is greate in verye deade, but yet it is ſuche as they may well ynough deceyue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues with al. For of theyr hope they haue no ſure triall at all. With this hope I ſay, the continuall enemie of mankynge kepeth man in ſinne won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, and by ſettynge forth to him the mercy of god, bryngeth him vnto this paſſe that he feareth not the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of god at all. But verely I ſay vnto you, that lyke as god granteth forgeuenes at the fyrſte to the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunte,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:16"/> and moſt fatherly ſheweth his mercy vnto ſuch as be conuerted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym: ſo doth he alſo ſharpelye pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe thoſe men whiche do contynue obſtinatly in vyce. Suche men then as repente not vnfeynedly, conceyue a falſe hope of the mercy of god. But the deuyl notwithſtanding by ſetting forth to men this hope, bryngeth this thyng to paſſe, that they liue on forth quietly, and ſecurly in vice and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, nor thyncke erneſtely with them ſelues at any tyme of any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or amendment. Yea, they deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe thabundaunce and riches of the bountifulnes and longe ſufferyng of god, beynge ignoraunt, that the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of god dothe induce, and leade vnto repentaunce: as Paule teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In this place alſo let vs cal that thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> vnto remembraunce, whiche our ſauiour ſpeaketh of in S. Mat. Repent, bycauſe the kyngedome of
<pb facs="tcp:4762:17"/> god is at hand: And alſo that which the lorde ſpake by the mouth of his prophete Eſai. Vnto whome ſhulde I haue reſpecte, but vnto ſuche as repente, and are lowe in ſpirite, and feare my commaundementes? In S. Luke alſo he declareth the ſame thynge: Excepte ye repente ye are al of you vtterly caſte awaye: And in the actes. Peter ſayth in this wyſe: repente therefore, and be conuerted, that your ſinnes may be taken away Here I myght allege infinite places of ſcripture, which make very plaine<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for this purpoſe, that no man, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che dothe not vnfeinedly repent, can conceyue certain hope to haue remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſynnes, which I wyl omi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> at this tyme. For as I haue ſayde al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy, he loketh in vayne for to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forgeuenes at gods hande, which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truely repenteth not with his herte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And althoughe there is no tyme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:17"/> repentaunce late in gods ſyght: As appeareth by thexample of the thefe which is ſpoken of in ſcripture: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo god wyll not the death of a ſinner but that he repente, and lyue: yet who may not ſe, howe daungerous a thynge it is to differ the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of our lyfe, ſith that there is no man (as the poete ſayth) in ſuche fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god, that he can aſſure hym ſelfe of the next morowe folowyng. For many times death crepeth, &amp; ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vppon vs: when we loke leaſte for it: ſo that than there is no tyme of repentaunce lefte, nor ſpace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and amende our lyuiug. Here I thynke it nedes to ſpeake of thoſe thinges which Plinius maketh men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of in his naturall hiſtory, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge ſodayne deathe, ſence that there is nothing almoſt in our tyme more common than the ſame. For not longe ago two olde men of oure
<pb facs="tcp:4762:18"/> countrey: which dwelte bothe in one cytye, dyed ſodaynlye vppon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne nyght, whan they dyd reſorte vnto a certayne woman: that they were wonte to company with all: the one dyed of a ſodayne paſſion: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was thruſt through with a dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: And nere nother of them euer ſpake worde after that tyme: Nowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let euery man iudge for him ſelfe, in what daunger theſe twayne dyed. And thoughe it be a thyng common as well to the godly, as vngodly, to dye ſodaynly. And the iuſte can not be, but in good ſtate, what deathe ſo euer they dye: yet verely a man can not deuiſe, how horryble a thynge it is for one to dye thus, which is with out repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of howe many haue we herde whiche were ſlayne oute of hande by multyplyenge wordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other ruffyans in tauernes whiche haue bene taken in bed with
<pb facs="tcp:4762:18"/> other mens wyues, or haue bene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyſe ſodaynly caſt away by one meanes, or other, in gamnyng or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe? to paſſe by thoſe, whiche haue broken theyr neckes of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe: haue peryſhed ſodaynlye by ſhypwreake: and haue bene oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the ruyne and fallynge of houſes vppon them, or with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch chaunces? Let vs then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte this, that god wolde haue the ſinner to repente rather than to dye: as he vndoubtedly wolde: yet by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vncertayne chaunces we can not without gret danger diferre the reformation of our life: yea though we put our hope firmely in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and goodnes of god. we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente therfore while we liue vppon yearthe, and be luſtie and haue our helthe: but the world is cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. For we ſe daily that the yonge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man giueth him ſelfe to belly chere,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:19"/> drinkinge and riotte: he flaterethe him ſelfe, and ſaith to him ſelfe that he maye liue many yeres, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore myndeth not any thynge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendemente of his life: but differreth and putteth that thinge of, vntill his olde age: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto whether he ſhall euer attayne, or neuer: it is harde for any man to ſaye: For tell me one of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes, which hath lyued vntil that age, but for his pleaſure let vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte that he may lyue ſoo longe as he wold wyſhe. What doth he than? I praye you, goeth he about any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation or amendment of his life? No no. This is euer more his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: I wyll amende to morowe, to morowe. And thus with ſuch delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge he flatereth, and deceiueth him ſelfe at length: for he is vncertayne, euen as al other be, whether god wil permit hym to lyue vntyll the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:4762:19"/> nyghte, or not: much leſſe is he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of the nexte morowe. Thus whiles a man differreth the reforma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of his lyfe, often tymes deathe ſodaynly ſtealeth vpon hym: As we may dayly ſe by experience: And yet we can not be admoniſhed and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by other mens perilles and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to take heede. The deuyll lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs on forthe, and feadeth vs in ſuche wyſe with vayne hope, of the mercie of god, and of longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lyfe.</p>
                  <p>But here though it can not be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor ought to be denyed, but that the repentant receiueth of gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie at all tymes: nor that he nedeth to feare or fal into deſperation, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is at the very poynt of death: yet I recken, that there is none ſo foliſh that he wyll choſe that thynge which is ieoperdſome, and leaue the other, wherin there is no daungere at all. Wherfore that noo ſuche feare or
<pb facs="tcp:4762:20"/> grudge of conſcience remaine, let vs goo about the reformation herof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times: nor differre it in any maner wiſe: ſythe that we are vncertaine of the nexte morowe folowing. And as towchynge the mercye of god, let vs remembre continually the ſaiyng of Ciprian. So much as god is (ſayth he) euer bountious, and merciful for his fatherly loue, and tendernes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs: ſo muche oughte we to feare and dreade hym, for the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of a iudge: that he beareth.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſhall it come to paſſe, that through the feare of gods wrath we ſhalbe withdrawen, and brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vyce, and ſhall not yet throughe the hope of his mercy be deceyued, and corrupted in ſecuritie. A worlde it is to conſider, how the popyſhe preſtes, flatter theym ſelues with this ſelfe ſame hope of goddes mercy, whiche kepe concubines al the days of their
<pb facs="tcp:4762:20"/> lyfe: and lyue-vnder the pretence of ſingle lyfe in moſte ſhamefull whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and abomination: nor thynke erneſtly with them ſelues of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation at any tyme: or of diſchar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge them ſelues of theyr whores. And thoughe they be giltie in theyr own conſcience of this theyr vicious and abomynable lyuynge, yet they go to theyr maſſe ſacrifice euery day and do alſo reſort and preſume vnto the lordes table, as they do take it to be. They eate the lordes breade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely: and drynke vnworthely of the lordes cup. Oh lord: how danger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and horrible is it to lyue in that ſtate, wherin if death ſhulde preuent a man: he were vtterly condempned, and caſt away both body and ſowle. Thoſe than, that after this maner kepe whoores all the dayes of theyr lyfe, and do in the ſame thyng obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately continue, nor purpoſe at any
<pb facs="tcp:4762:21"/> tyme to diſmis theyr ſtrumpets: nor truely do repent and crie god mercy with ſighynge and teares, for their wicked and ſynfull life, doo flatter them ſelfe falſely with this hope.</p>
                  <p>But here peraduenture ſome man wyll obiecte this, and ſaye. What? good ſyr, do they not cry god mercye oftentimes? and beſeche him to haue mercy vpon them: do they not dayly ſay in theyr euenſong? Conuert vs (Lorde) and turne thine angre from vs? Alſo in the later ende of theyr matines, lord haue mercy vpon vs. I ſe farther they pray in many other places, that it wil pleaſe god to haue mercye, ſpare and forgyue them? I here your reaſons very well: Nor I entende not to axe you the queſtion or reaſon with you in this place, how they praye? or with what entente of mynde: or what zele, or what feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſpirite? But admit, that they
<pb facs="tcp:4762:21"/> pray with an ardent deuotion, and a mynde erecte, and lyfte vppe to god: with moſt erneſt affection, what can ye conclude herevpon? For what pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyteth it them, onles they diſcharge them of theyr harlots in that minde, purpoſe neuer to receyue theym agayne, and in that purpoſe to lyue chaſtly, and contynue euen to thend? But for ſo muche, as they do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente (as we ſee playnely) ſurely we nede not to doubt, but that they ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holde it to be a fable, whiche is taught in ſcripture, of the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, or els fondly flatter them ſeues with this hope of the mercy of god.</p>
                  <p>Oh yl fauored, and horrible face of that the popiſhe churche. Such as ſhulde rule, teache, and inſtructe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not ſo much by their learning, as example in lyuynge, become ſoo diſſolute, that in theym others take greate cauſe of offence. Marke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentely
<pb facs="tcp:4762:22"/> the laye men, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire vnto the myſticall table of the lorde: how reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, with what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration in confeſſyng their ſins. &amp;c. with what godly behauour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocion they come? how diligently la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ure they, and endeuour that noo grudge remayne behind in their con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience? how certaynly purpoſe they thenſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orth to amend that, whiche is amiſſe, &amp; to refourme theyr lyuynge? but conſyder now, what our whoriſhe maſmongers commonly vſe to doo. Verelye (as one of theyr order wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) they come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thimbraſcinge of a whore vnto the aulter, and that not ones or twyſe, but often and day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, without any punyſſhemente or ſhame. They paſſe not for any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they mynde not to diſcharge theym of theyr whores. No ſygne of repentaunce foloweth of the reknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legynge of theyr faultes: and to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:4762:22"/> the verye truthe, they ſeme to be in name onely chriſtians: in deade ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heathen, and publicans. Than ſome man wyll are of me, whether there be any hope that ſuche ſhalbe ſaued, or not. Verely to ſpeake my conlcyence: I thynke that they can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyue no hope of the mercy of god, bycauſe S. Paule affirmeth vnto the Hebrewes, that god wyll iudge whorkepers &amp; adulterers: And doth plainly denye that thoſe ſhall be the inhericers of the kyngdome of god. Nowe if the preſtes of Balaan per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade theym ſelfe, that Paule dyd ſpeake the truthe, as it can not be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nied but he dydde: can they in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che abomination, and fylthy liuing, conceyue any hope of ſaluation: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidering that they neyther do repent vnfeinedly, nor purpoſe to diſcharge theim of theyr minions? but if they doo not beleue S. Paule, we take
<pb facs="tcp:4762:23"/> them to be chriſtians amiſſe, for they ar no more to be taken for Chriſtians than the heathen and publicanes are, like as our ſauiour ſayth. By what lawe or authoritte do the byſhops the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffre ſuch abominable liuers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue within their iuriſdictions &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſes? why licence they ſuch men by theyr aucthoritie to preache in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: wherfore do they wynke at ſuch abominacion, and permitte them for bryb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to vſe yerely ſuch whordome? This thyng is ſo manifeſt, that it can not be denyed, ſo fylthye, and cryed out on, that it is not lawfull to beare with it. And it can not be couered, or cloked anye longer. Thoughe than they wyl ſay, that they are not playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vngodly: bycauſe they attrybut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> honoure to the name of god, yet it is manifeſt, that they can not be, taken for godly: bycauſe they giue them ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues to ſuch thynges, as are moſt co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:4762:23"/> to godlineſſe, like as Hilarius affirmeth, where he wryteth of ſuche. And ſurely ſuche are they alſo, which are not greued and offended with the abominable liuyng of thoſe, and open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly do deteſt the vndefiled &amp; pure bed, as S. Paule calleth it: that is, the honeſt and laweful matrimony of the myniſters of the congregation. Oh terrible thynge to be harde: oh miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and lamentable ſtate of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. O lorde Ieſus, come and ſuccour thy churche, which ſo long as the popiſſhe kingedome endured, had ſuch paſtours and myniſters, as were almoſt faythles. But ſome man wyl peraduenture contrarye me, and ſay, that they beleue to be ſaued by Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes benefite: wel, that I ſtande not in this poynte with you: admitte that it be ſoo as ye ſaye. Nowe beleue they S. Paule, where he affirmeth that whorekepers and adulterers ſhal not
<pb facs="tcp:4762:24"/> be inheritours of the kyngedome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> god? I thynke not the contrary, but they beleue it, for we oughte not to thinke the contrarye. Sithen then theſe men be of that numbre whome Paule denieth ſhall be inheritours of the kyngdome of god, or the holy ghooſt rather. (The thynge muſt be graunted of neceſſitie, whiche can be denyed in no wyſe) how can they pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe them ſelues ſaluation, in Chriſt By this reaſon then they beleue that they them ſelues ſhall be ſaued: and whorkepers, ſuch as they are in very dede, ſhalbe condempned: Lord for thy mercy what ignoraunte blyndes is here, what lacke of iudgement is this? do they not ſe plainly, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeake contraries? If they may hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any ſure hope to be ſaued, then tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Paule wryteth vnto the Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans: is falſe: but if that be a great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ouerſyghte, and an abſurde thyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:24"/> to affirme, theſe men can conceiue no certayne, and aſſured hope, or truſt, that the father is pleaſed with them for Chriſtes ſake. Than what truſte is this? how thinke they, to be ſaued, They that haue but ſmall ſyght in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique, maye eaſely ſe, howe ſtronge, and pythy our reaſon is. The fyrſte part in logique termed Maior, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of S. Paule: for he ſayth, that whoorekepers, and adulterers ſhall not be inheriters of the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god: The ſeconde parte cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Minor, is confirmed, and verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the whole worlde: for they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce with one aſſent, that our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtes are ſuch: Of theſe twayne then the Catholike may frame ſuche a concluſion: that all the packe of papiſtes lyuynge in abhominable whoredome are baniſhed men out of the kyngedome of heauen: All men thoughe they be but ſklender logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb facs="tcp:4762:25"/> ſe very well, that this is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary concluſion, which is brought in and gathered of the former prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are manyfeſt true, and graunted of our aduerſaries. This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is faſhioned in the fyrſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and fourth mode. Therfore the popiſhe priſtes liuynge in ſuche abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable whoredome can conceyue none aſſured hope, and truſte of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, nor haue true fayth, as they feygne, thoughe they bragge and ſpreade abrode certayne vncredible tales of theyr faythe: but ſome man wyll peraduenture obiecte, and ſay: that it maye come to paſſe, that ſuche as lyue wickedly and vngodly this day, may to morowe, or after, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it ſhall pleaſe the goodnes of God repent, and acknowlege their ſinnes and after the reknowlegynge thero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lyue innocentely, and in the feare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> god: therfore we ought not ſo lyght<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:25"/> to deſpeire of the ſaluation of any man. I haue weyed your reaſon dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently: and no doubt of it, we may ſe, howe ſuche men ſtudie the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of theyr life, and how truely and vnfeynedly they repente. For where haue you ſene heretofore of many thouſandes but one, which ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge ſuche remorſe of conſcience, hath forſaken his whore, and fullye purpoſed neuer after that tyme to company with her? I wote well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe what I ſay: for it is euident and knowne. There is ſcarſely one of euery thouſand that caſteth thus with him ſelfe, for to amende his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and to forſake his whore in good erneſt, and with his harte. But nowe to leaue theſe thynges: howe ſtynkyng and abominable is the out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde face of that popyſhe churche: wherein the ſuperintendaunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> miniſters do lyue in ſuch open abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:26"/> ſoo that others are not a lyttle offended therewith? What a thyng is it, when whorkepers muſt exhorte men to chaſtytie: the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent to repentaunce, the wycked to godly lyuynge? yet this thynge is done dayly, as we may ſe: not onely in vyllagies, but in gret cyties: and peraduenture alſo in ſome regions, but without al queſtion it is done in all landes, all places, where ſo euer the pope is ſupreme heade: the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes them ſelues lokynge on, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittynge, and almoſt approuyng it: whiche thynge bycauſe they ſharply punyſhe not, as by theyr offyce they are bounden to doo, but for brybes ſuffer men to lyue in moſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whordome, they encourage them to take pleaſure, and delyght in the thynge, and do ſette them forwarde, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought to brydle, and kepe backe: yea they be the cauſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:4762:26"/> though the preeſtes lyue in ſuch abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination, yet they thynke it no ſinne at all, and them ſelues do miniſter to the ſame occaſion by ſufferinge them to continue obſtinatly in ſuch whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Of the which one thynge, as of theyr other cure and offyce, they ſhal render a ſtreyght accompte, and reckenynge, but here ſome man wyll axe me, what were the byſhops dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye in this behalfe: I wyll tell you, it were none other but this: not to winke, and diſſemble in ſuch abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon (as S. Paule exorteth) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet to permitte it, or beare with it. Fyrſt they ſhuld admoniſhe them and reproue the vice of whoredome. Than if they profyted nothynge by ſo doynge, the nexte remedy were to put them out, and let them haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge to doo in the congregation, and to excominicate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of their temples and ſacred places, And to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:27"/> caſt out of the aſſembles of faythful men, ſuche as are adiudged to hell fyre: and to giue them (as Paul wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth) into Satans handes to morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie theyr fleſhe, that in the day of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte they myghte be ſaued. I ſay that this were their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: if they ſhulde execute the ſame, and approue theyr doynges in the lordes ſyght, which is the ſelfe ſame iudge, that wyll requyre, and haue an accompte of all theyr doynges.</p>
                  <p>They ſhulde ſhewe them ſelues au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and example gyuers of good workes, and an example of the fayth full aſwell in theyr communication and conuerſation, as alſo in loue, ſpirite, fayth, and purenes of lyfe. But ſithe that nowe a dayes, the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops commonly ſhewe them ſelues ſuch to the inferiour ſorte of the clar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie, yea and rather worſe than the ſame is, by theyr example they do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:27"/> not onelye cauſe, but alſo encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the ignorant fooles to offende more boldely a greate deale then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyſe they wolde, for they thinke that they may boldly by the byſhops example do ſo. Yet I wonder much at it, that they can not be awaked, and ſterred to repentaunce, ſence that they haue ſo many, and ſundry occaſions thervnto: For theyr office is to viſet, comforte, confeſſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle the ſycke: To miniſter the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the bodye, and bloude of the lorde, and the laſte vnction, to be preſent with the ſycke at theyr death and departure: To ſynge dyryges, in the which there is mencion made ſo many tymes of the day of anger, of the daye of calamitie, of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull daye: of the fearfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of god, of eternall condempna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: of the theſe, whiche repented late, in the which alſo they ſeke, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:28"/> pray, that they fele not the peines of death, nor be bounde with the cheine of ſynne. And beſydes all this they gyue attendaunce to the beere, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inge the funerall maſſe, and burye the deade, omittyng no ceremonies: yea, euen when they walke in theyr temples, and churches, they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and reade Epitaphies grauen vpon graues and tombes, whereby they might be admoniſhed, not only of me that be deade, but alſo of death it ſelfe: whiche dayelye and hourely hangeth ouer theyr heades: alſo of the laſte dowme, of the iudgemente ſeate of the lorde, and ſuche other.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer in theyr Requiem maſſe they are warned of the comynge of Chriſt: of the reſurrection at the laſt day, of the voyce of the archaungell, of the trumpe of god. &amp;c. Therfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſyth that theſe thynges can not be a warnyng ſufficient for them, &amp; cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:28"/> them to repent, of two thynges, the one muſte be the cauſe without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: eyther that they thynke thoſe thynges to be but fables, whiche be taughte vs in ſcripture, of the laſte dowme, and are in the Epicures opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſowles be not immortall: or els that they flatter theim ſelues, as I haue ſhewed with falſe hope of the mercy of god.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="cause">
                  <head>¶ The thirde cauſe.</head>
                  <p>I Fynde that the thyrde cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is the cuſtome of ſynne, which is in a maner, made natural in long continuance. For lyke as it is harde for a manne to alter nature, ſoo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, if it be ones roted, can not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely be plucked vppe and expelled: And therefore it is that lerned men do cal cuſtom an other nature. It is not very much diſagreynge fro this
<pb facs="tcp:4762:29"/> purpoſe, that a certayne man ſayth. Such vyces as we haue accuſtomed our ſelues to, from our tender age, can not be without greate difficultie weded out afterwarde, which thinge though it be very certayne and true, yet who ſeeth not howe fondelye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bringe vp theyr chyldren in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keryng, and pamperyng them? for from theyr infancy they be gyuen to no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e other thynge, but to delicious fare, and to the beallye pleaſures of the bodye: They refrayne not from vnſemely and baudy talkynge: they ſweare and blaſpheme god: they go ruffelynge in theyr gorgeous geare and trype in theyr purples: They weare cotes of diuerſe colours, hoſe cut and pounced out with ſarcenets. Yet I omitte the gardynge of theyr cotes, which is very folyſhe: for there cometh no profitte at all therof, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore what thynge ſoo euer they
<pb facs="tcp:4762:29"/> do, they do it fearſlye, hardely, and boldely: There is in them no myld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor ſobrenes: They exhibet not dewe honour to theyr parentes: they do not reuerence aged men, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theyr egalles, and companions: what wyll ye more: they thynke, that what ſo euer they do, they may do it without blame. There is in them no ſhame, noo feare of god at all, that can withdrawe them fro vyce: They paſſe for no honeſtie, and vertuous lyuynge, and leſſe a greate deale for religion and doynge theyr duetye to godwarde. Yea parentes theim ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues now a dayes with euyl example corrupte theyr chyldren, ſo that they can not by theyr corrections brynge them into feare of them, nor by they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> commaundement withdrawe theym fro that, that they ſet theyr myndes on: whan ſurely they ſhulde do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, when theyr chyldren are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:4762:30"/> that were not lawful to be done, nor ſay any thynge, that myghte not honeſtely be ſpoken. Theyr lyuynge ſhoulde be ſo godlye and vertuous, that therwith theyr chyldren myght be moued to ſuch lyke: their maners, and conuerſacion ſhuld be ſuch, that therby theyr chyldren myght learne, when ſo euer they had reſpecte, vnto the ſame, bothe what they ſhulde fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and enbrace: or fle and eſchew. But when the father dothe expreſlye declare that thynge in his owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which he reproueth in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, doth he not, whyles he blameth them, accuſe hym ſelfe? What face can he haue to fynde faulte with his chyldren. which with his yl example corrupteth them? How can he ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reproue any vyce in his children which may fynde in hym ſelfe vyces more worthy to be reproued? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let parentes remembre, that it
<pb facs="tcp:4762:30"/> is theyr dewtye, and very requiſet in them, to lyue withoute blame, and vertuouſly: and that for diuers cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both leſt they be example to their chyldren of naughtynes: and that they may iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly reproue vices in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laſt of all that throughe theyr ſlacke negligence the aucthorite of fathers be not diminiſhed. Thus much is declared by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which the poete ſayth: Howe canſt thou take the aucthorite of a father in correctynge thy chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whan beyng an olde man thou thy ſelfe committeſte offences bothe more heynous, and worthy of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Such a lyke thyng Nauſiſtrata ſaythe in Terence, where ſhe repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her huſbande, bycauſe he was greued with his ſonne, which haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Stewes: and yet he was a greate deale more to be blamed hym ſelfe: what iuſt cauſe haſt thou (ſaith ſhe) to chyde hym? To theſe is Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones
<pb facs="tcp:4762:31"/> ſayenge in Plaut. agreable. Is it meate for a father to geue yll example to his children, art thou not aſhamed. Let vs note alſo, what was broughte in the declamacion of the yonge man agaynſt his father, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he accuſed of madnes: father ſaythe he, the I blame, and none but the for all my riote, and bycauſe thou brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte me not vppe vnder the lawe of a well ordered houſe, nor kepeſte me in feare and awe, wherewith I mought haue bene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawen frome ſuch vices, as raygne moſt common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in yonge men. Yea thou was a ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter on, and leader vnto ſuch vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines. But this Tobye an holy man and derely beloued of god dyd not, whiche taught his ſon (as his hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry declareth) euen of a chylde bothe the feare of god, and alſo to refreine from vyce: he was him ſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of godly lyuing, to his ſonne: he
<pb facs="tcp:4762:31"/> buſied him ſelfe to declare him ſuch one to his ſonne in euery condicion as he wyſhed to haue hym. But now a dayes whan youth ſhuld be traded and brought vp in good learnynge and gods word, how be they occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: verely I am aſhamed to ſpeke it: yet I wyll not diſſemble with them, for very conſcyence ſake I am enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and driuen to it ſore agaynſt my wyll, I take god to recorde. Moſte part of teachers (I do not ſpeake ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of all) do gyue theyr ſcholers ſo muche of the brydle, and ſuche ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye, and al to procure and wynne the loue, and frendſhyp of theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, or at leſt not to diſpleaſe, and offend them, that they put it in their choyſe whether they wyll learne, or not, neyther refrayne they them fro vyce by ſharpe correction, nor cauſe them to profitte by graue admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: They trade theym not in the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:32"/> knowledge, and feare of god, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe them in modeſtie &amp; other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, beſides that ſuche innocencie &amp; ſtreyghtnes appeare the not in theyr owne maners, as is requiſite, nor ſuch humanitie, and gentylnes, as ſhulde be in ſuche, as beare the perſon and reſemble fathers, but to much ſlackenes, and negligence, as they were companions, and play <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes rather then teachers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructours. And by ſuch liberte with out punyſhemente, theyr ſcolers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not onely diſpiſets of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and teachers, but alſo fearſe, ſelfwylled, negligent, ſowleyne, and ſtubbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne. Yt is neadles to ſpeake ought of theyr prodigious apparel, of theyr vndecent and vnſembly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauioure: of theyr boſtynge, theyr braggynge, and iettynge vp, and downe with theyr rapers, and hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe clokes: of theyr prodigal, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:32"/> large ſpendynge, euen when theyr techers loke on, and ſe it wel ynough but diſſemble and wynke at it, more ouer of theyr contynuall riottynge, feaſtynge, banketynge, playenge, daunſynge, quaffynge all the nyght longe and watchynge that I ſpeake not of other good felowſhyp, that is amonge them? Of this, which I ſay I am certayne: for theyr diſſolute ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge is ſuch, that it can not be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, nor hyd, nor yet excuſed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner wyſe. Wherfore ſyth that mayſters, permitte and geue ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte to the youth, wherof they haue the charge and ouerſyght, as to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente, and vſe ſuche naughtines, and to fall headlonge into all kynde of enormities, which ſhulde moſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, diligently, and ſtreyghtly bridle and ſnaffle theyr impudent boldenes and ſuppreſſe and bring downe their fearſe and great hertes, and reſtrein and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:33"/> breke the wylde riottous youth with good leſſons, graue warnynges and corrections: what hope may there be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued of ſuch, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal come to mo yeares, and be more at theyr owne ſwynge, and lybertie? Of all lykelyhod it ſhulde be thus, that he which from his chyldhod hath bene trayned in vyce, ſhall not withoute greate difficulte become vertuous, and godly afterwarde, nor that he, which of a chylde hath bene an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrift, ſhalbe eaſely reformed, whan he commeth to full yeres, and mans ſtate: it taketh ſuch place in vs, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto we haue bene accuſtomed from our tender age, like as the poete ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Agayne ſuch thinges the mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forgetteth not lyghly, as it hath ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of longe tyme: I wolde wyſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with al myne herte, and I pray god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that al townes, and cities wolde w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ponder, and wey this matter, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:33"/> wolde not be led by affections in cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge a teacher, and menne for theyr youth, nor haue in this behalfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte to kynred, and frendſhyp, or to the commendations, and requeſtes of frendes. Surely this is a great and weyghty matter, ſo that men ought not to admitte, and take a maſter for euery iacke gentilmans requeſt: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideringe that here vpon reſteth the whole welth of a realme. He ſhulde be an honeſt &amp; lerned man, whiche were able to teache, and trade them in the knowledge and feare of god, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in good lernynge, and moral ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. But neuertheleſſe it can not be expreſſed, how farre men be in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> poynte deceyued, which do not place &amp; preferre well learned men, ſuche as are for theyr honeſtie, and vertuous conuerſation and lyuynge, wel tryed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and for their conditions and man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s prayſe worthy, and knowen to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:4762:34"/> diligent, and peynfull in teaching and for theſe admitte a ſort of vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned curyfauours, ſuche as ſeke for none other thynge, but to be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure with noble men, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted worthy of preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> men to teache, and brynge vp theyr chyldren in good letters, and tonges when in very deade they be no more apte for that purpoſe then a cammel to daunce: as we ſaye commonlye in oure Englyſhe prouerbe. Suche fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe dreames they teache, as no ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or politique man beynge vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned could heare, but he muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to laugh: what rude felowe of the countre may not iudge it, wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge it diligently, to be very fond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and folyſhe. Suche is theyr igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in al kynde of good learning: And thoughe they be thus, yet they haue wonderfull meanes, to couer, and clooke it. But for as muche, as
<pb facs="tcp:4762:34"/> they can be of none authoritie, and reputacion for lacke of learnyng (for theſe thynges be atteyned by none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane, but by learnyng onely) they gyue theyr ſcolers in theyr ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to much lybertie, and by reaſon thereof corrupte, and marre theyr yonge, and tender wyttes. And this they do for none other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hyng, but to flatter them, and curifauoure. But lette vs returne vnto oure purpoſe. Syth therfore that bothe parentes, and alſo mayſters, and teachers do not onelye meynteyne, but cheryſhe, and cocker yonge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abes, and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch folly, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in ſuche vyce: and gyue them leaue to do, what ſo euer they lyſt, nor at any tyme endeuour to tame, &amp; ſnaffle their wyld appetites, what meruayle is it, if they be, founde thus naughty and vicious, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to theyr full yeares, and mans ſtate, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4762:35"/> haue of children ben trayned, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, with ſuche vyce? Specially if this be alſo conſidered, that cuſtome is altered in continuaunce of tyme in to nature: as we haue declared here tofore. Yf theſe men therfore at any tyme do fully purpoſe to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te them &amp; refourme theyr lyuynge: as when theyr conſcyence moueth them, or the burthen of their ſyn prycketh them? yet cuſtome hath ſo preuayled in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whether it be agaynſt theyr wyl, or not theyr knowledge, they daylye fal into worſe, and worſe enormities, and lyke madde men dyfferre the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatyon of theyr lyfe. Conſyder nowe I pray you, what ioly iunkers and luſty brutes theſe wyll be, when they ſhal come to be citizens, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedlers in matters of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: which by theyr fathers haue bene thus cokered, and by their teachers ſo niſely, and ſoftly vſed: nor
<pb facs="tcp:4762:35"/> haue ben kepte ſtrayghtlye to theyr learnyng, as they ſhulde haue bene? what other thynge but this, is the cauſe of it, that there be nowe of day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſo many adulterers, deflourers of mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, baudy and pernicious ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyans? that we haue ſuche plenty of diſſers, charders? &amp; that ſuch wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; abomynable lyuers are ſprede about in euerye quarter, but onelye naughty education, and bryngynge vp: well than, ſuche as impute this thynge to the newe learnynge, hadde nede of a purgation to pourge theyr brayne, and the powers of theyr wit: for be lyke the humoures fall downe in ſuch aboundance, that their ſyght is ſtopped: ſo that they are not able to iudge of thynges. No no, the new lernynge hereof is not the cauſe, but naughty bryngynge vp, as I haue declared: the ſlacknes and vnredy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the maieſtrate to do, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb facs="tcp:4762:36"/> his offyce: for in this place I ſpeake not of kynges, and prynces: Yf magiſtrates I ſay, wolde ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſtreightly punyſhe offenders without any berynge with them, nor fauoure other part in any wyſe: then we ſhulde ſe better order euery where and among all ſtates of men. If the lawe whiche was made by Iulius, and is named commonlye Iulia lex, were called agayne, which doth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe adultri with death, nor permit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth fornication to lacke iuſt peine, &amp; deſerued puniſhment: if alſo ſuch as abuſe the name of god, as they that ſpeake blaſphemye agaynſt god, and ſwere by Chriſt his croſſe, his woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and bloude: If they that vſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes, playenge, and walke vp and downe in tyme of a ſermon: if diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediente chyldren, that exhibite not dewe honour to theyr parentes: If theues, morderers, diſſers, raueners
<pb facs="tcp:4762:36"/> robbers, vſerers, iuglers, dronker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, gluttons, &amp; ſuch as haue ſpent, and made a way theyr lyuyng in bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chere, and vnthriftines. Yf ſklaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derers, ſcolders, ſuch as be periured and reporters of vayne tales: And finally if al offenders were ſtreyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly punyſhed, ſurely there ſhulde be both leſſe occaſion geuen to offende, and alſo good men ſhulde not haue ſo greate cauſe to complayne of the maners of men of this age. Let the magiſtrate therefore remembre his office, and thinke that he muſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye gyue an accompte at the daye of dowme. Lette him learne of Paule that he bearethe not his temporall ſwearde for ryght naught, for he is gods miniſter, appoynted of god to punyſhe offenders: As it appeareth playnlye vnto the Romaynes. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche then, as Paule declarethe that a law was ordeyned not for iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:37"/> men, but the vnrighteous: for the diſobedient, lyers, ſuch as intyce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſeruantes from them, and are periured: foraſmuch alſo as the magiſtrate in this behalfe is as it were a miniſter of the lawe, certes he can not be ſlacke in executynge his offyce, without great reprofe. Lette poteſtates therfore, thoſe I meane, that are in offyce, and haue authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, reſtrayne this libertie to offende, without punyſhment, by one meane or an other, which thynge yf they do not execute: they do very naught: &amp; it wyll be vndoubtedly layd to theyr charge, at the laſt day. Who ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth not men to offende, when he may, in a maner commaundeth them ſo to do: I feare me greatly, leſt the heathen mens ſeueritie, &amp; ſtreyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in punyſhyng vyce ſhalbe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche to vs, and accuſe at the laſte dowme our neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ſlacknes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:37"/> herein. There was amonge them punyſhment ordeyned, and appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the lawe for all offenders, and treſpaſſers: They had theyr ſonmers theyr examiners, and iudges, which dyd moſt rigorouſly ſe vice, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes punyſhed. Thus were fearſe and wylde felowes for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhement kept backe from the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde acte: for feare of punyſhment, they brydled, &amp; brought theyr wylde affections into ſubiection: for feare of punyſhment, they conquered, and ouercame theyr luſtes: and ſo ranne not headlynge into vyce? But nowe a dayes by a reaſon of libertie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out punyſhemente, and ſlackenes of men in offyce, which forgyue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at the fyrſt, nor do punyſhe vice ſo ſeuerely, as they ſhuld do, a blynd man may ſe, how much the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and polycy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is fallen away, and decayed: No man cauſeth lych<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:38"/> be punyſhed: no not adultrye, and fautes, which are very heynous. No man correctethe the dyſobedyence of chyldren towardes theyr parentes, the ſtyfe rebellyon of inferyoures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt heades and ſuperiours, the detractacyon, &amp; refuſing of laweful impery, and authorite. No man ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a reſtreynt for ſuperfluous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell: No man repreſſeth the lyght and madde conceyte of men, &amp; pryde not onelye for theyr gorgious, and kyngelyke arraymente, but alſo for the dyuerſitie of coloures, for cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, and gardynge theyr garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. No man reſtreyneth theyr large expences, and coſtes in theyr breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtes, theyr dinners, and ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuppers: And though they drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke both nyght and day, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge ſayde to it. No man punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth carders, dieſſers, vſerers, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſers, ſkolders, curſers, the periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:38"/> and ſuch as ſpeake blaſphemye agaynſt god: And yet I haue not touched the common ſtewes in euery cytye, the lybertie permitted within the byſhoppe of Romes dioceſes to kepe whores: and impunitie of all vyces, and enormities. Men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie therfore ſhuld w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute all de lay punyſhe ſuch: not that it is an of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence to do ſo, but that all occaſyon to do yll myght be remoued: and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye. In puniſhyng thre thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, be chyfly to be conſydered: firſt that thou ſtudye his reformation, whome thou punyſſheſt: Than that by his example thou make a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers frome commyttynge the lyke offences: Thyrdly, and laſt of al, that by weadynge out the naughtye &amp; vn godly, the innocente may lyue at reſt &amp; in quietnes. Hitherto ſtatutꝭ haue profited nothing: we muſt now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take an other waye. And here let
<pb facs="tcp:4762:39"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s conſider that the magiſtrate bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not his ſwerde for a ſhewe: As Paul witneſſeth: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede requireth therfore, let him drawe it to punyſhe and cut awaye vice, and let not men long cry for theyr redines &amp; prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in executyng theyr office, whiche are in auctoritie, and do intermedle in ſuche matters that in as muche, as perteyneth vnto the outward po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we be not founde wors, than the Heathen, and gyue, and miniſtre by our ſlacknes to the enemyes of the goſpel, and Chriſtian name occaſion to ſklaunder, and ſpeke yl by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as it happeth manye tymes: Howe wolde ye haue the turkes to thynke, that our relygyon is good, ſyth that the profeſſours &amp; teachers of it are ſo vicious, and abominable vndoubtedly they may iuſtly, and by good ryght hit in our teach &amp; obiecte to vs ſo many riottours (as one
<pb facs="tcp:4762:39"/> certayne man ſay the) ſo many dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerdes, aduouterers, fornycatours and whoryſhe ruffyans, ſo that we in very deade may be greatly aſhamed of our behalfe. They wyll and may muche agaynſt our vyces: they wyl alſo as they iuſtly may, fynde faulte with and reproue oure ſuperfluitie: They wyll and may laye to vs for a reproch, our beaſtely &amp; voluptuous lyuynge. And thus by reaſon of our vyces, and our yl lyuyng, the worde ſhalbe diffamed: And as Paul ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the name of god ſhalbe ſklaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered amonge the Heathen, for oure ſakes. And though riot is a vyce of euery tyme, and age, &amp; hath ſo ben, and belly chere alſo, as breakefaſtes deyntye dynners, ſumptuous ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, exceſſe in meate and drynke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aduoutry fornycation violent wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge, and oppreſſynge of the pore, by powers: the neglectyng of good
<pb facs="tcp:4762:40"/> lawes, and ordinaunces, whiche we fynde, that euery learned man repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in men of his tyme (lyke as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca affirmed, that none age was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer voyde of all blame) yet in our tyme vyces haue wonderfully encre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and not onelye vyces, but alſo the impunitie of vyce, whiche is the origine, &amp; cauſe of vice. Good order is nowſet at naught, youth is corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by to much lybertye, all kynde of wyckednes is growen vp, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed wonderfully, ſo that vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes ſelfe, and Epicuriſme ſemeth to haue inuaded, and occupyed a place amonge men, and poſſeſſed a kyngedome, amonge Chryſtyans. Men do lytle regarde good lawes, &amp; ordynaunces: but do al together fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe pleaſure, and carnall lybertye. Wherfore it were the offyce, &amp; dewty of kynges, and byſhops by theyr au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to withſtande ſuch enormy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:4762:40"/> and to remedye them: ſyth that for this cauſe they were exalted, and called vnto ſuch an hyghe dignitie, and god wolde that they ſhulde excel in myght, and power. He commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them to haue theyr people in ſubiection, and to loke ouer them, as though they were ſet vppe on an hyghe mountayne, to eſpye out vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and enormities, and moſt rygo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to reſtreyne, and punyſhe the ſame, &amp; to defende the godly, &amp; feare the naughtye from theyr vyce by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere punyſhment, and to defend and meynteyne iuſtice and truth, and ſet forth and dilate the religion, &amp; glory of god: Wherfore let them remembre theyr offyce, and though they can not cleane extirpate, and abolyſhe ſuche enormities, as haue crepte in, and are roted in mens hertes: yet at leaſt let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go about to reſtreine the ſame And though it conſiſteth not in them
<pb facs="tcp:4762:41"/> to make other men godly, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (for that is the worke and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of the holy ghoſt) let them yet in deuour to brynge this to paſſe, and effecte, that we be not founde eyther Pagans or wors, then they be. And lette magyſtrates charge parentes ſtreightly with this thinge, that they do ſe theyr children traded &amp; brought vp in good learnyng, and alſo in the knoweledge, and feare of god euen from theyr chyldhod. For ſurely the magiſtrate ought moſt of all to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayle in this thynge, ſyth that it is a thynge ſo profytable for the common welth, &amp; the preſeruation of townes, and cytyes reſteth in this one thynge chefly. Yf they lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed but to this one thynge dylygentlye, and executed theyr offyce herein, we ſhulde not be troubled with ſuche vyces, as haue heretofore reygned, and yet raygne in many places: which thynge vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
<pb facs="tcp:4762:41"/> can not be prouided for, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtatutes, or lawes: but onelye by this meane, whiche I haue ſhewed, that is to wytte by the godly educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bryngynge vp of youthe. For ſyth that lawes punyſhe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alredy commytted: godly educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, letteth a man to commytte any thynge worthye of punyſhemente: Lawes do but correcte vyces, godly education kepeth them farre of and ſuffereth no ſuch thynge to be: it is very euidente, that godly education doth more profyt the common welth, then lawes, and Statutes do. It is commonlye ſene in oure tyme, that ſuche as haue bene broughte vp in vyce, are not refreined, and brought in feare by the punyſhement, whiche the lawe ordeyneth and appoynteth for vyce, and enormities. This was the cauſe therfore that prudent, and wyſe rulers were wonte to laboure,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:42"/> and trauayle herein chiefly, &amp; haue theyr ſpecyal care on this one thinge not alonely how to punyſhe vice, but howe to preuente and take away the cauſes thereof. Whiche thynge by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they dyd ſe, myght the beſt be broughte to paſſe, if youth ſhulde be brought vp in good learnynge, and in the feare of god: and yf fathers imployed theyr diligence, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to the ſame ende: they thought it beſt to labour, and trauayle chefly therein: But from this dygreſſyon lette vs returne agayne vnto oure purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="cause">
                  <head>¶ The fourth cauſe.</head>
                  <p>I Fynde that welth, and proſperitie is the fourth cauſe whiche dothe inebriate the myndes of men, in ſuch wyſe that they neyther reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre god, nor conſtantly purpoſe to refourme
<pb facs="tcp:4762:42"/> and amende theyr lyuynge: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one auncient wryter ſayth very wel: that lyke as of proſperitie riotte procedeth: euen ſo of riotte commeth both other common vyces, and alſo vngodlynes, and the neglectynge of gods worde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandementes. And Seneca affyrmeth, that into greate welthe and proſperitie, as it were continuall dronkennes, men fall into a certayne ſoote, and ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte ſteape. Alſo Paule vnto Timothe commaundethe that this admonition and warnyng be geuen to the rych, that they wax not proud nor put theyr affyaunce in vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ryches, but in the lyuynge god to do good, &amp; be ryche in good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. This verſe of Publius may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be verified of the inordinate rych men. Fortune maketh hym a foole, whome ſhe kockereth to muche. For howe, ſuche paſſe for no manner of
<pb facs="tcp:4762:43"/> thynge, whiche haue this worlde at wyl: it is euydent ynough, and nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it is to ſpeake therof. This ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie is verely the mother of al vyce, for by the ſame a man is made vnſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſo that in his conſcience he fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not the anger, and wrath of god agaynſt ſynne: by ſecuritie mennes myndes are brought on a dead ſlepe that they be not a whyt perced with the feare of the punyſhment of god, or withdrawen from vyce, nor yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked with the feare of deathe, or of the laſt dowme. Our ſauiour dothe in Luke artificially paynt this ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, where as mencion is made of the rych man, which when his lande had enryched, and made hym welthy with a frutfull, and plentyfull crop, dyd not go about to refourme his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and to repente, nor to beſtow almes vpon the poore, but ſtudyed howe for to enlarge his barnes, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:43"/> to make more roume for his corne: and thus delayted the matter with hym ſelfe. I wyll brynge in, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon heapes all my corne, and lay vp al my ſubſtaunce, and ryches and ſpeake to my ſowle in this wiſe Nowe thou haſt my ſoule a greate deale layde vp for the, whiche wyll laſte the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſpace of manye yeares: Nowe therfore take thy reſte, eate: drynke and be of good chere. But in this ſecuritie, and this imagination what herde he of god? Thou foole, this nyght requyre they thy ſowle of the: markeſt thou not, howe deathe commeth ſodaynly vpon hym, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge to haue had all the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and pleaſures of the worlde: as eaſe, reſt, delicious fare, paſtymes, delectacions, and ſauegarde of all his goods? For this cauſe then, as Paule ſayth: commaundethe vs to awake, &amp; be in a redines at al tymes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:44"/> agaynſt the commynge of the lorde: which myght be a fayre &amp; ſufficiente warnynge for vs, yf we take heade of it, for lyke as it befell and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the time of Noe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the floud ouer went, and drowned the worlde, ſome eatynge and drynkynge, other ſome weddynge, and doynge ſuche buſines as they had to do: As it alſo chaunced, that the Sodomites were al deſtroyed with fyre and brymſtone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, after that Loth departed out of theyr cytie, ſo verely the laſte daye ſhal come ſodaynely, and at the twincklynge of an eye, euen when men loke leaſte for it. Therefore S. Iames to vanquiſhe, and dryue ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch ſecuritie oute of mennes hertes ſpeaketh to ryche men in this wyſe. Ye ryche men mourne, and owle for the miſeries, that remayne for you, and hange ouer your heades. Your ryches putrifie, wormes, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:44"/> corrupte your gorgious appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel: your ſyluer and golde gathereth ruſt, and cancte: deliciouſly, and wantonly ye haue lyued on yearth: Ye haue ſpente your dayes in ryot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge. &amp;c. In this place call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the rych man in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, whiche in the dayes of his lyfe we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gorgiouſly arayed with his vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets, purples, &amp; ſilkes, but after his death he was greuouſly tormented in hell, wherof proſperitie &amp; welth was the cauſe, whiche dyd not permytte and ſuffer hym to repente, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme his lyuynge. Our ſauioure alſo declareth the ſame thyng in S. Mathewe, where he ſaythe that it is hard for one that is rych, to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter into the kyngdome of heauen, eftſoones it is more eaſe for a cammell to paſſe throughe the eye of a nedle, then for a ryche man to entre into the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god: which Marke in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:4762:45"/> expowneth: Chyldren, ſayenge howe harde a thynge is it for ſuche one, as putteth his truſt in ryches, to entre into the kyngdome of god? Chriſt alſo hym ſelfe calleth ryches, and worldely pleaſures, brambles, &amp; bryers, wherwith the ſeede of gods worde is choked, that it can not growe, and bryng forth fruite. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore this is the cauſe, why god ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes viſiteth with aduerſitie and pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eth them, whom he hath dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued: to roote out ſecuritie, &amp; to ſtere vp in men the feare of god, and the callynge vpon his name: for in proſperitie men do cleane forgette hym: Alſo to cauſe vs to acknowlege and confeſſe our ſynnes, and repente therfore, to lyfte vp and erecte oure myndes to the imbraſing of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thynges, and the contempnynge of worldely thynges. For common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe vices raigne in rych, and wel
<pb facs="tcp:4762:45"/> thy men: and thoſe that lyue in this worlde at theyr owne eaſe: I meane ſluggyſhnes, which is reckened one of the .vii. deadly ſynnes: idlenes, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernes, ſodayne priuation of ſenſe, and felynge, and neglecte, and lytle regarde of thinges perteyning vnto god: in godly and vertuous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, vnluſtines, ſlowenes, dulnes, feyntnes, and as it were a dead ſlepe except thou wilt cal it rather that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe which engendreth in the body a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynual deſyer of ſlepyng. This ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie is ſuch an abominable vyce, that I am not able with theſe names and infynyte other to declare howe heynous it is, and what I thynke of it. Scripture declareth that welth makethe vs not onely ſecure, but oftentymes vngodly, where vppon Moyſes ſayde thus. But when he was become fat, and fylled, he waxed wanton: when he was made groſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:46"/> corſye, and vnweldye, he dyd cleane forſake the lorde his god, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure: he regarded not the rocke of his ſaluacion: They prouoked him in ſtraunge gods. &amp;c. Lyke as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd after that he had conquered his enemies in euery lande, fallynge in to this ſelfe ſame ſecuritie, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge that al thynges were ſure and in ſafegarde, dyd not onely become an adulterer, but alſo defyled his handes with ſhedynge the bloude of an innocent man: and the very ſame which in the perſecution of Saule ſhewed, and proued him ſelfe a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, by proſperitie was cleane al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered? Let hym therfore, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on his feete, beware leſte he fal. Yea, when Dauyd had commytted this cruell morder, as thoughe there had bene no daunger therin, bycauſe god is mercyfull, he wente vnto the tabernacle dayelye as other dyd, he
<pb facs="tcp:4762:46"/> kepte the Sabboth, &amp; other feaſtes which were at that tyme obſerued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Iewes: he offered vp ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and finally was quiete, and toke no care. But after that god by his prophet Nathan denounced his punyſhment, and vengeaunce: and had made him afearde, and had gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly threatened hym, he came to hym ſelfe, and then called to mynde, what an offence he had commytted agaynſte the lorde his god: Then pondered and weied he the greatnes of his ſynne, and repented vnfeined<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Then he confeſſed his ſinne open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and cried for mercy vnto the god of Iſraell. Then wyſhed he to be waſſhed from his ſynne, and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to be pourged fro the fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, wherof his ſyn was the cauſe And yet in the meane whyle refuſed he not the punyſhement whiche god by the prophet threatned to hym: nor
<pb facs="tcp:4762:47"/> forſoke any payne or punyſhemente for his offence and treſpas: wolde god, that ſuche lyke ſecuritie myght not alſo be founde in manye of vs, which do lyue ſo quietly and in ſuche ſecuritie, as though al were ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and there were no daunger: we confeſſe not oure ſynnes: we feare not the iudgemente of god, nor his exceding greate wrath agaynſt ſynne: ſo farre of is it, that we bewayle oure ſynnes and haue remorſe in oure conſcience for them as we ſhulde haue, lyke, as the holy martyr of god Cyprian ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. But to returne agayne vnto our purpoſe, &amp; couclude in fewe wordes No man can be ſaued onles his ſinne be remitted: No mans ſinnes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but theyrs whiche crye, and pray to god for the remiſſion therof: No man deſyreth remyſſyon, whiche wold not be gladly reconciled, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolde gladly be reconciled: whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4762:47"/> repenteth not: No manne repenteth whiche feeleth not the wrathe of god agaynſt ſynne, &amp; confeſſeth the ſame which thynge he that lyueth in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, doth not. By this reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is euydent that proſperitie is alſo a cauſe of delayenge the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our lyfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="cause">
                  <head>¶ The .v. cauſe.</head>
                  <p>THe .v. cauſe is the hope of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger lyfe: for albeit there is no man, thoughe he be neuer ſo yonge, that is aſſured, that he ſhal lyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll nyght tyde (as Cicero ſheweth) yet verely thou ſhalt ſcarſly find any man ſo olde, and aged, whiche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth not hym ſelfe that he maye lyue a whol yere. The olde father in the commedye cryeth out, and ſayth: Moue, and exhorte ye me, which am lxv. yeres olde, to marye agayne, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4762:48"/> ioyne vnto me an olde dotynge wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? But nowe a dayes ye ſhall ſo a more ſtraunge thynge: for men that be .lxxx. yere olde wyll marye, &amp; take to wyues yonge maydens, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles that are not ouer .xv. yere of age. They haue ſuche hope to lyue longer and longer: as though they were yonge men, and in there flowri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing age, but with what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thus do, experience oftentymes ſheweth. Some ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will meruail par aduenture, that olde men ſhuld be ſo foolyſhe, as to be come wowers. In this place I wyll not reaſone, eyther to, or fro: but I dare be bolde to ſay, that ſuche olde men, as marye yonge damſelles after this maner, haue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubtedly hope to lyue a great tyme longer. This hope therfore maye be an other of the cauſes: why we differ the reformacion of our lyfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not, that we haue an acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:48"/> to make at the laſt daye. It is to be wondred, that men do put of, &amp; differ thus, ſuche a great &amp; weyghty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and loke no more of a thynge, whiche profiteth ſo muche, and is ſo neceſſarie vnto ſaluation. I feare me greatly leſt the Heathen ſhall in the laſt iudgement be a reproche to vs Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in that we are ſo flowth full, and haue almoſte mynde at no tyme to refourme, and amende oure lyuyng, &amp; torecken vp our offences and repent: when verely manye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after Pithagoras rule, cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, yea they went to reſt, reckened, and called to remembraunce what thyng ſo euer they had ſayd, or done, good or badde, the day before: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Virgil ſpeaking of a godly, and vertuous man, paynteth oute to vs very artificially, and lernedly. He neuer ſlepte, before that he called to remembraunce all thynges, that he
<pb facs="tcp:4762:49"/> dyd that day: whether it were good, or bad: he examined, what was done amiſſe: what was done in tyme, and what out of tyme, he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne queſtions of him ſelfe in ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable wyſe, why haddeſt thou not reſpecte in this poynte vnto honeſtie in that poynte vnto reaſon? what thynge hathe this daye eſcaped the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> why haſt thou purpoſed conſtantly that thynge, which were much better to be lefte vndone: why haſt thou ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed in thyne harte to haue done good to the poore? why wylleſt thou that thynge, which it was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, nor honeſt to wyll? why preferredſt thou profytte to honeſtie why ſpeakeſt thou yll by any, or ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt an yl ſigne in thy countenaunce, why haſte thou folowed rather thy folyſhe fantaſie, then ryghte reaſon. Virgill ſheweth that when he hadde thus reuolued, what he had done all
<pb facs="tcp:4762:49"/> the day longe: whether good, or bad; he rebuked that, which was euyl, and prayſed, and commended the good. In this place I can not let paſſe that which Seneca ſpeaketh, concernyng this forme, and trade. Sextius (ſaith he) at the euening, yer he went to reſt, accuſtomed to axe of his mynde cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne queſtions ſemblably: what yll and naughtye condition haſte thou this day amended. What vyce haſt thou with ſtande? what art thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nowe, then when thou diddeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſe? And after he addeth this. What better forme can there be, than this: to examine the whole day agayne in this wyſe? Muſte not there folowe after ſuch a rekenyng a ſweat, ſownd quiet, free, and pleaſaunt ſleape, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mynde is eyther prayſed: or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and is taken to be a iudge, and examiner of it ſelfe? I my ſelfe vſe this trade, dayly, and reaſon in this
<pb facs="tcp:4762:50"/> wyſe with my ſelfe: as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. When the day is paſt: I examine the whole agayne, and ponder, and wey depely both what I haue ſayd, &amp; done: I kepe nothynge in ſecrete: I omitte nothynge, for why ſhulde I be affrayed, ſyth that I may frely ſay take heade: do no more ſo, for at this tyme I forgyue the. In thy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with ſuche a man thou dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt reaſon conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiouſly: hereafter I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the, diſpute not with the igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant. Thou warnedſt ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more frely a greate deall, then thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: and more offendedeſt hym, then correctedeſt hym. Henceforth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder not onely: whether thou ſpeake trueth, or not, but whether or no he can beare it, to whome it is tolde. Seneca ſpake theſe thynges, and many mo in this ſentence, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, which I wolde wyſhe, that chriſtians wolde not onely remembre
<pb facs="tcp:4762:50"/> but alſo purpoſe, &amp; caſt to folow and to bring vp, and trade theyr children in this fourme of exercyſe. Certes onles I am very farre deceyued, we ſhulde then endeuour to leade our lyfe more agreably to our profeſſion But now of the contrary let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder our exerciſes, and howe we vſe to recken our fautes, and examyne the whole day agayne at nyghte yer we go to reſt: howe are we occupied? Verely we kepe ioly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here one with an other, our tables are furnyſhed with deyntye diſhes: And we are not contente to drynke, and ſwyll in, all the day longe, ercept we banket, and drynke alſo at nyght, where vppon what vyces procede, we be none of vs ignoraunt: And at laſt when we are not thorowlye ſatiſfied in dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, we aryſe frome the table in ſuch caſe, that we can not ſtande on our feete, but ſtagger, and ſtumble
<pb facs="tcp:4762:51"/> at euery thynge, and muſte be ledde home, and ſtayed on other mennes ſhulders. Oftentymes we fall into ſuch beaſtlynes, that we muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fro the table and layed in oure beddes by others: And there we lye lyke brute beaſtes drowned, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed with wine, and ſleape. I can not with more propre wordes ſette forth this abomination. And this is a thynge that is done daylye. But ſcarſly ones we do in a whole yere re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compte, and recken with our ſelues, howe we haue lyued, &amp; axe forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ſynne, and purpoſe to be reconciled to god. And yf peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we purpoſe ſo, yet trueth it is, we continewe not therin: ſo farre of is it that we do dayly euery man trye and examyne his owne conſcyence, &amp; conſyder howe he lyueth, yer he go to bed: And beynge offended and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with hym ſelfe ſeketh god to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:51"/> haue mercy vpon him, with ſyghing and wepyng, or putting his affyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and truſt in god, truſteth and promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth him ſelfe that is better in Chriſt: or if he purpoſe to lyue godly, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth therein: And yet for all this we dare boldely ſleape, and take our reſt in that ſtate, in which if any man ſhulde dye, as no man is ſure, that he ſhall lyue vntyll the next morowe, folowing, we were vtterly caſt away, and condempned both body &amp; ſoule. But alas theſe thynges we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre not: In ſuch wyſe we flatter oure ſelfe with hope of longer lyfe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſyth that ſo many men be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, howe chyldyſhe are we, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther howe do we dote, which do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues, that we be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, out of the nombre of thoſe, as it were by ſome ſynguler, and propre priuilege.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="cause">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4762:52"/>
                  <head>¶ The .vi. cauſe.</head>
                  <p>THe ſyxte cauſe remayneth: and that why welthy, and ryche men within the biſhop of Romes domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons differre the reformation, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menmente of theyr lyfe, the cauſe is hope of forgyuenes of ſynnes by the Popes Pardons, and bulles. Alſo a certayne falſe truſte to releſe the paynes of purgatorye by maſſes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigies ſayd yerely, preſtes, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes prayers, and alſo by the workes &amp; almes dedes done by theyr frendes alyue, as faſtynge, prayenge, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge, and goynge of pylgrymage and ſuch lyke. For lyke as certayne men affyrme that pardonnes haue ſtrength to obteyne temyſſyon of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: ſo are they not aſhamed to ſaye that in what moment of the houre ſo euer a penny, or money gynglethe in the boxe, the ſoule at that verye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb facs="tcp:4762:52"/> doth depart out of purgatory: and more ouer they thinke that the deade are eaſed by the good workes and merites of men alyue: whiche Hilarius vpon Mathewe doth deny And ſo doth Hierome, as he is alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the common law, affyrme that in this preſent lyfe one may helpe an other, whether it be with his prayer, or good councell. But at what tyme we ſhall appeare before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente ſeate of the lorde, euery man ſhal beare his owne burthen, beſides this in what ſtate ſo euer a man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he ſhalbe iudged in the ſelfe ſame ſtate. Then howe deteſtable is the ſluggyſhnes of ſuch men, as lyue thus quietly, and ſecurely in vyce, &amp; wyckednes? which wolde ywyſſe, yf they regarded ought theyr ſaluacion and ſoules helth, kepe ſome meane and not ſo excede in vyce as they do, and remembre the laſte dowme: As
<pb facs="tcp:4762:53"/> for an example, to ſpeake perticular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the vncharitable man wold ſtudy accordyng to gods commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to be at atonement, and agremente with his neygheboure: whorkepers, and adulteres wold remembre, that god wyll iudge them: As Paule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth: Alſo murderers, ſuch as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter poyſon to others, all ſortes of lyers wold haue before theyr eyes the lake burnynge with fyre, and brym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, wherin theyr parte ſhalbe, as we reade in the reuelations of Iohn Couetous men, drunkerdes, ſklaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of theyr neyghboures wolde remembre, that ſuch as they are, ſhal not be inheritours of the kyngdome of God: As Paule wytneſſeth bothe vnto the Cor. and Ephe. Rych men wolde beare in mynde the ſayenge of Chriſte, that he whiche putteth his truſt in vncertayne ryches, ſhall not entre into the kyngdome of god: fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb facs="tcp:4762:53"/> al men wold reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and vnquenchable fyre of hell, which Chriſt threatneth in his worde to the wycked, and vngodly: euery man wolde feare the voyce of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to the folyſhe women. I know you not, and to the ſlowe ſeruaunte: caſt the vnprofitable ſeruaunte into the outwarde darkenes, where there ſhalbe wepynge and gnaſſhynge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eath: Alſo to the man that came to the maryage without his weddyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> garment, bynd hym both hande, and foote, and caſt him into the outward darknes. Alſo to the wicked, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly at the laſt day, departe fro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urſed into euerlaſtyng fyre. O good lorde what obſtinate, and ſtyffe felowes be theſe, that ſuch ſaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges do nothyng ſtere? we may cal them that beleue them not, Epicures: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that deride, and haue them in mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, vnhappie, and ſuch as regard
<pb facs="tcp:4762:54"/> them not, madde, and lytle conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge theyr ſoules health. But all thoſe regard them not which thinke that when they haue brought oute a rablement of the popes pardonnes, they may frely ſinne, and offend with out punyſhment, and by reaſon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of dilay, &amp; put of from tyme to tyme the refourmation and amendmente of theyr lyfe. There be manye alſo that differre the ſame, bycauſe they worſhyp Barbara: And thoſe be in this fonde, and folyſhe opinion, that they thynke verely, and beleue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, that they ſhal not dye impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente, and without howſle, as they terme it, yf they worſhyp her. This ſuperſticious worſhyppynge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Barbara was placed almoſt in all the papyſtes hertes: therfore they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned yerely a faſtyng day for her. And paynters portraied her in thone hande bearyng a chalyce. And in the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:54"/> other holy breade. This is alſo an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, bicauſe men prouide long yer they dye, that they may be recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the famylye of the Francyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes, and be buryed in one of theyr robes after theyr death. For men be of ſuch a foliſhe perſuaſion, that they thynke the deuyll to haue no power ouer them, when they ſhal haue g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that holy hyue ouer theyr heades bycauſe the Monkes communycate with the robe both theyr owne meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: and ſuch good workes alſo, as are doone throughout the whole or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as requiem maſſes, ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſeruyce, ſinging<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> praieng, preaching, ſuffrages, faſtynges, watchynges, pylgremages, and ſuch lyke. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Monkes dyd ſette euer aparte that thing, which was thought ſufficient for their owne ſalua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, and the reſt yf that any remayned, they dyd not communicate for right nought, but
<pb facs="tcp:4762:55"/> ſolde it for money. This is therefore another cauſe, why that ſuch men as haue boughte out with money the merites of Monkes, dyfferre in this wyſe the reformacyon of theyr lyfe. But nowe it is nedeles to confute in this place this groſſe errour, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the popes pardons, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppynge of ſayntes, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatynge of merites: ſyth that other men before vs, and we alſo our ſelfe haue done it in other places. Nowe thou haſt herde gentyll reader, as I thinke the principal cauſes of dilay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge the amendment of our life. But beſides theſe there are yet certaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it were ſecondarye cauſes: As to accompanye with the wycked, and vngodly, and ſuche as ſtande in no feare of God, and eſteme not, nor regarde vertuous innocencye, and thoſe thynges, which are agreable to our profeſſyon for ſuche mens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pani,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:55"/> al thoſe muſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly eſchewe, whiche haue any care of their ſoules health: For as a certaine man ſayth full trulye: yll company rorrupteth good manners. And yf thou accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyeſt with the euyll, incontynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of tyme thou ſhalte thy ſelfe be come euyl. Let parentes therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre, that it is their deuty to loke to it, that the euyll, and naughty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companye not theyr chyldren: and to try exactly the maners of ſuch, as ar theyr playfelowes. For ſuche they proue moſt commonly, as theyr play felowes be. So that here this maye be a good leſſon for vs: yf a man wyl not be fyled, let hym touche no tarre, which ſignifieth naughtye company in this place. Lette vs marke alſo, what an Hethen man ſayth: we take and receaue our condicyons of ſuche as we accompany withal. And as cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne vices of the bodye be contagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:4762:56"/> and do infect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we touch, ſo tranſferreth the mynde vices vnto ſuch, as we daylye accompanye with all, and are oure famylyers. The dronkerde prouoketh his felowes to wyne drynckynge. The vnchaſte goeth about to ouercome the chaſte. The couetouſe man allureth his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyons vnto auaryce. &amp;c. Who ſo wyll lyue godly therefore: let hym eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe euyll company. For if therebe any, that acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany ſuch, and be day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye conuerſaunt with them at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, and at other places, wher they reſorte. They do neuer lightlye pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to refourme there liuinge: No. They can not without much dyfficul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie be brought from their companye at any tyme. And this is the cauſe, that thoughe they here Gods worde preched neuer ſo much: thoughe they be admoniſhed and warned by men in auctorite neuer ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:56"/> they them ſelues eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fully determine, and purpoſe to reforme, and amende their liuinge, bycauſe they feare and drede the puniſſhement of god: yet I can not tel howe the deuyll it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, they differ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually the amend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of there lyfe: they repente not: nor retourne into the waye agayne. And thus peraduenture deathe may come vpon them in ſuch ſecurite, and oppreſſe them. For euen as death is moſt certeyne: ſo the daye, and houre of death is vncertayne: And for this cauſe we be commaunded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to awake and watche, and be in readines for the laſt day euery hour which thyng is planely ſette forth in Luke: where it is ſaid ſemblablye be in a redines: bicauſe the ſon of man wyl come, when ye ſhall leaſt weene. There is alſo another cauſe: why the lay ſorte commonly dyffer the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion of their lyfe: forther there be
<pb facs="tcp:4762:57"/> certeine men good ſoules, and fauou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers of gods worde withal theyr hert (we may not iudge the contrary) but not ſo wyttie in this one poyntt, as were nedeful: which ſet forth wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully, and beate into mennes heades the grace, and goodnes of God: the forgyuenes of ſynne: and many ſuch other thinges, whiche perteyne vnto ſaluacyon: And for this purpoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage ſcriptures very dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly: But of a newe lyfe in Ieſus Chryſt, that we be made holy, and reuiued by the holy ghoſt, they neuer ſpeake worde or verye lytel. But he that wyl be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as a chriſten man muſt, as Paul wylleth hym, be dead to ſynne, and a lyue to ryghtuouſnes, he muſt lay of the old man, and put on him the new man. He muſt be as perteinyng vnto his conuerſacyon euen as one, that profeſſeth the Goſpell of Chryſt. He muſt not be an aduouterer, a whor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:57"/> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, an enuious felow to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bor warde. He muſt not be couetous, giuen to filthy gaine, and lucre, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, or proud. The father gyueth the holye ghoſt to thoſe, that beleue and cal vpon him: which wyl awake the herte of man, and ſtere vppe in it newe mocyons, and as it were rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate his wyll: and moue him to do good woorkes: to lyue vertuouſly and agreablye to our profeſſyon, as we haue declared in other places more at large. Howe much thynkeſt thou, be the laye people moued with ſuche ſaienges, as theſe are. What? yf thou be an adulterer, an whoore keaper, a couetouſe man, or ſuche: beleue onelye, and thou ſhalte be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: why ſhuldeſt thou fere the lawe ſyth that Chriſt hath fulfilled it, and ſatyſfyed for the ſynnes of the whole worlde? vereſy ſuch ſaienges do won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e offende the eares of Godly
<pb facs="tcp:4762:58"/> men, and giue occaſion of much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly liuing: and beſides that, cauſe men, that they thinke but lytel of any reformacion. Ye mary it is the cauſe that they contynue obſtynatelye in vice, nor that all one, but alſo be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged there vnto. Surelye it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away al the occaſion of reforma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion. Wel Paul did not thus: whiche dyd not onelye preache the fayeth in Chriſt to Felix, and Drufille hꝭ wyfe (as Luke declareth in Thactes) but alſo reaſoned profoundlye of iuſtice, temperance, and the laſt iudgement, ſo that Felix herynge hym diſpute ſo exactely, &amp; to the purpoſe was muche abaſhed. He alſo teſtifieth in thactes that he dyd not preache repentaunce onely to the Heathen, but alſo gaue them warnynge, that they ſhulde do workes worthy of repentance. Nowe I haue ſhewed you the cauſes why we difer the reformacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>fe. It
<pb facs="tcp:4762:58"/> remaineth therfore, that we ſhewe in lyke maner brefely, what be the reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies for the ſame, whiche partelye we haue done alredye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="remedies">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The remedies.</head>
               <div n="1" type="remedy">
                  <p>THauthoritie therfore of god, and our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt ſhalbe of muche force, and power agaynſte our vnbeleue, concernynge the laſte iudgement, the punyſſhement of the wycked, and the euerlaſtynge bleſſe, of the godly: onleſſe we wyl rather be taken for Chriſtians, than be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans in very deede: ſpecially yf we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly wey, and cal to remembrance thoſe thinges, which are mencyoned euery where in ſcripture concernyng the ſame thinges. As this ſaienge in Saynt Iohn. The houre ſhal come, when t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey, which are in their graues ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his voyce. And ſuche as
<pb facs="tcp:4762:59"/> haue done wel, ſhall aryſe vnto lyfe: but they that haue done the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, ſhal aryſe vnto condempnacyon: Againe, the wyll of my father whiche ſent me, is this, that whoſoeuer ſeeth me, and dothe beleue in hym, ſhall haue euerlaſting lyfe: and at the laſt day I wyll rayſe hym. Our ſauyour alſo in Mathewe, ſpeakynge of the laſt iudgement declareth, what ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he wyll pronounce of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and ſaieth thus: O ye, which are the bleſſed of my father, poſſeſſe the kyngdome prepared for you frome the beginning of the worlde: but the vngodly ſhall here this. Auaunte y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the accurſed: go ye fro me into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge fyer: which is ordeyned for the deuyl, and his Aungels. Againe: theſe ſhal go to euerlaſting fier. But the iuſt, and Godlye to euerlaſtynge life. Oh what a terrible voice is this of the iudge, that adiudgeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:4762:59"/> to euerlaſtynge fyer. Yf the feare of iudgement here in yearth maketh ſuch aferde, and aſtonied, as are gyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye: muche more muſt the feare, and dreed of the heauenlye iudge make them aſtonied: and the gylte of theyr owne conſcience. If that thou dredeſt here in earth the iudge, from whom thou mayſte appeale vnto an other, much more haſt thou cauſe to dreade the ſentence of that iudge, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom there can be none appealynge at all. This is his ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Go fro me: O ye the accurſed. How heuy, and dredful a thynge is it to be banyſſhed out of gods ſyght, which in goodnes farre paſſeth, and ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth al thinges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> howe miſerable a thing is it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded out of the kyngdome of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is ſuche, that we can not yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the pleaſure of it, much leſſe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnto it in wordes? Howe lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table a thinge is it to be priued of the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:60"/> company of ſaintes, and godlye men? But we ſhal not only be ſecluded out of the kingdome of heauen, that moſt ioyful, &amp; bleſſed habitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhalbe alſo appoyncted to infinyte peynes in hel, and vnquenchable fier, which paſſeth our fiere ſo many degrees in heate, that in compariſon of it this is veray yſe. There ſhal we accompa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny continuallye deuylles without all hope of a better ſtate. Thinkeſt thou if men remembred theſe thinges that they wolde lyue ſo wickedlye, as they do? vndoutedly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they thinke lytle. As Peter declareth in thactes, that god the father, hath ordeyned Chryſte to iudge the quycke, and deade: whiche thynge alſo Paul noteth both vnto Timothe: and alſo vnto the Corin. Theſe be his wordes. Al we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pere before the iudgement ſeat of the Lord: there euery man to receaue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingelye as he hath done here in
<pb facs="tcp:4762:60"/> earth: eyther good: or the contrarye, In this iudgement (as he alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) what thynge ſoeuer hath benne hyd, and couered, ſhalbe reueled, and dyſcloſed to the whole worlde: which thing howe terrible, and ſhamfull it wyl be to the wicked: no tongue is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſay, or mynde to thinke. For yf here in erth a man had rather be ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed quicke into the grounde, than haue his fautes opened, and ſhewed afore a great multytude of all ſtates of men, which might be wytneſſes of his wretchednes: what hertes ſhal the deuelyſſhe haue than: thynke we, when all thynges, whiche they haue either purpoſed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceued, or wrought ſhalbe dyſcloſed, &amp; tolde to the whole worlde, to the Angels in heauen and to all ſaintes, and other. If we iudge it a ſhameful thynge to be ledde into priſon here in earth: how much more ſhameful a thinge wyl it be to be caſt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:61"/> into euerlaſtyng fier? If it be a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing to be banyſhed here in erth or to ſuffer death: howe muche more terrible wyl it be to be exiled and out lawed fro the kyngdome of heauen: and the bodye, and ſoule to be puny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with endles death? If it ſhalbe a glad, and ioyful herynge, when the ſon of god commaundeth the godlye to pertake, and poſſeſſe the kingdom prepared for them frome the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde: of the contrarye, howe heuy newes wyll theſe be to the wicked: when they ſhal here them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues adiudged to the vnquencheable fyer ordeyned for the deuyll, and his aungels? If thoſe thinges we beleue to be true, which the ſcripture ſetteth forth concernynge the laſte iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and paine of the wycked: Why liue we ſo, as thoughe there were nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther heauen nor hel? If we beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not: why wil we be taken for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.
<pb facs="tcp:4762:61"/> Let vs therfore put awai, &amp; expel theſe domeſtical vices, .i. lithernes, and ſlugyſhenes: for our ſtrife is not bout the Goates woole (as it is ſaid in the common prouerbe): But al the whole matter is about our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the atteynement of the heauenly and bleſſed life. Nowe therfore let vs refourme our lyuynge: nowe I ſaye, whyles we haue the whole tyme for forgiuenes, and haue him our medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and aduocate, whiche at the laſt day ſhal iudge vs. Let vs not defer the amendment of our life, vntil ſuch tyme, as our ſin ſhall ſeeme rather to haue lefte vs, then we to haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it. Let vs dayly, and hourely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the day of dowme, the terry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voice of the iudge, whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the wicked to depart, and auaunte from hym: Let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber alſo the paines of hel, and of the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les fier. Let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the ſhortnes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:62"/> and vncertainte of lyfe: certaine deth and yet that the houre therof is moſt vncertaine: ſo that in ſuch vncerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te a man can not promes him ſelfe that he ſhall lyue, but one moment of an hour: a great dele leſſe a day or twain Therefore this is an excellent, and a very notable ſaieng of Seneca. For as much as thou knoweſt not, when, or where thou ſhalt die: therfore loke thou for death in euery place: and at al times. In this wiſe I wyl conclud then, that the ſhorter, and vncertener mans lyfe is, ſo much the more ſhuld we repent, and refourme our lyuing, whyles we haue yet tyme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="remedy">
                  <head>¶ The ſeconde remedy.</head>
                  <p>NOwe to ſay ſome thynge in the ſeconde cauſe, we ſhulde nat in any wyſe differre the reformation of our lyfe, for that hope &amp; truſte, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:4762:62"/> we haue in the mercy, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god: Chriſt came to call ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: But to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their former life, and not to ſyn more frely, &amp; more at lybertie. As god is mercyfull ſo doth he mercifully forgyue: But the repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunt, &amp; not the obſtinate in ſin. Chriſt bare our ſynnes on his owne body to the croſſe: as Peter ſayth: I do not deny: but what foloweth? that we mortifyenge our fleſhe ſhulde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue to ryghtuouſnes. Chriſte gaue him ſelfe for vs: as Paul reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth vnto Titu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I denye not, but what dothe immediatly folowe? That he myght redeme vs from our ſynne, &amp; pourge a choſen people for him ſelfe to do good workes. Chriſte pourged vs by his bloude ſhed frome ſynne: As Iohn declareth in his Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? I graunt that to: but nat that we ſhuld pollute our ſelfe agayne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fylthynes of ſyn. We haue Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:63"/> our aduocate with the father. But if we repent vs of our former lyfe, and ſo reſorte vnto hym for ſuccoure. Thou wylt peraduenture ſaye, that I maye well ynoughe here after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle my ſynnefull lyfe. To this I anſwer: Howe knoweſt thou, that thou ſhalt lyue but a moment? much leſſe canſt thou haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope to lyue, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll thou mayſt repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and refourme thy lyuyng. Conſyder with thy ſelfe what the lorde ſayde to the rych man in the goſpell: that in proſperitie promiſed hym ſelfe manye yeres to lyue. O foole: they ſhal requyre this nyght thy ſowle of the. Thou haſte nede to take heade, leſte the ſame chaunce alſo to the. Thou ſayeſt: but I hope better. But what if this hope begyle you: for here I may cry out. Oh deceyptfull hope. Now if it hap ſo, which thynge god prohibite: thou ſhalt peryſhe, and wylfully caſt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:63"/> thy ſelfe into euerlaſtynge deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This thou wylt not agayne ſay, but that in ſuch vncertenty of lyfe it may well come to paſſe. What follye then is it by dilayenge to putte that thynge on ſyx, and ſeuen, whiche at the firſt thou myghteſte prouyde for, without al daunger? why doeſt thou not repent betymes, rather then hope thus with ſuch ieoperdy. Thou wilt ſay to me. God is mercyfull: Truth it is, but he is alſo iuſte. Then ſyth that thou truſteſt ſo much in his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye: why feareſt thou not lykewyſe his iuſtyce. The lorde ſpeaketh by his prophet ſemblably. I wil not the death of a ſynner, well, but what fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: that he be conuerted, &amp; lyue. Therfore be conuerted vnto the lord (as Ioell exorteth the) with all thine herte, in faſting, ſighing, and teares, be conuerted vnto the lorde thy god. For he is bountifull, gentyll, longe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:64"/> ſufferynge, and of much mercy: As the ſame Ioell ſayth. This thynge dyd alſo Ezechiell declare: Where he ſayth. If the ſynner ſhall repent him of his ſinnes, &amp; kepe my commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and execute iuſtyce, and iudgemente, he ſhall lyue, and not dye. Is it my wyll (ſayth the lorde god) that the ſynner rather dye, then be conuerted, and lyue? Alſo Eſaye. Let the ſinner forſake his waies, and the iuſt chaunge his wycked though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: and turne vnto the lord, and the lorde wyll haue mercy vpon hym: let him be conuerted vnto the lorde god of hoſtes: bicauſe he is great in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye. The Prophet declareth, that God is good, and mercyfull, but to the repentaunt, thoſe that acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge &amp; confeſſe theyr ſynnes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fyrſte repente: retourne agayne vnto helth: requyre forgyuenes of thy ſynnes with bytter teares, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:64"/> weapynge, be offended and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with thy ſinnes euen with al thin harte. Forſake thy former pathes, be conuerted vnto the lorde god: and then thou mayſt vndoubtedlye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a ſure hope, and truſt to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Then thou haſt no cauſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeire of the goodnes of god, and of the forgyuenes of thy ſynnes. And in the meane tyme call this to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce, which is ſpoken by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour that there is greater gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and gladnes for one repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunt ſinner: than is for .xcix. iuſt menne in theyr owne ſyght: Let this alſo ſtere the, bycauſe the Aungels be ſo glad, and wyſhe ſo hartely thy ſaluacyon. I haue bene wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully moued, and delyghted with the ſayenge of the Pſalmiſt. The lorde is good, and mercyfull, longe ſufferynge, and of much mercy. Note alſo what as he ſayeth in an other place. Thoſe thou
<pb facs="tcp:4762:65"/> hateſt (Lorde) which worke iniquitie, and thy countenaunce is fixed on the which do euyll: A man wyll perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſay to me, that Iohn affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that who ſo beleueth in the ſon hath euerlaſtynge lyfe: But the very ſelfe ſame Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dothe in an other place playnely pronounce, that who ſo ſynneth is of the deuyll: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who ſo ſayth, that he knoweth god, and kepeth not his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, is a lyer. But thou wylt ſay that Iohan the baptiſt teſtifyed this thyng of Chriſt: that he is the lambe of god, which taketh awaye the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the worlde. But what is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned immediatly there vnto: repente you of your former lyfe: eftſoones, brynge forth ſuch fruytes, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt ſhulde. But thou wylt yet go further with me, and ſay, that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: As we reade in the actes, ſayeth: We beleue that by the grace, and fre
<pb facs="tcp:4762:65"/> goodnes of our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt, we ſhalbe ſaued. That is plaine alſo, but what addeth he therunto: repente therefore, and be conuerted: to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that your ſin may be taken away and forgyuen you. Thou wylte ſaye agayne to me, that God ſo loued the worlde, as we may reede in S. Iohn, that he gaue his onely ſon that whoſo euer ſhulde beleue in hym, ſhulde not peryſſhe, but enioye euerlaſtinge lyfe: But nowe by your pacience, here me: what Math. ſaieth. Euery man, that ſaieth to me, Lorde, Lorde, ſhal not en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter into the kyngdome of heauen: but onely they, which do the wyl of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in heuen. If thou bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt S. Paul, where he ſaith: that Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners: beleue hi alſo, where he ſaieth that ſorcerers, adulterers, whoreke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, murderers, robbers, theaues, proude, and couetous men, dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kerdes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:66"/> ſklaunderers, ſowers of ſedicyon, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious folkes, and ſuch other ſhall not inherite the kingdome of god: yf thou beleueſt hym, where he ſaieth thou: no not Paul, but the holye ghoſt, rather ſpeaking in Paul: beleue him alſo in the tother: And than vndoutedly thou ſhalte conceiue none hope of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God in ſuch fylthy, and abomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable liuyng, nor yet loke for to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by Chriſt. For fayth grounded v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon gods worde confeſſeth this thing: that like as God is merciful to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt, ſo he is greuouſly offended with ſuch: as continewe obſtinatlye in ſyn. By the hope than of the mercye of God thou ſhuldeſt not dyffer, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmacion of thy lyfe: and therwith deceiue thy ſelfe: but retourne into the way agayne: and then myghteſt thou aſſuredly promiſe thy ſelfe very large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the mercy of God. For like as no man doth truely, and vnfaynedlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:66"/> except he truſteth to haue remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of his ſinnes: So verelye (as Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe ſayeth) no man can aſſure hym ſelfe of forgiuenes: except he dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, before I procede any further, I wyl recite one place out of Ieſus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach. Thou ſhalte not ſay: ſaith he: I haue offended, and what heuy thynge hath chaunced to me? for the Lorde is eaſy, and gentyl: heape not thou ſynne vpon ſinne, ſetting feare apart. Thou ſhalte not ſaye: his mercye is great: he wylbe merciful to me, and forgyue me my treſpaſſes: for as he is mercifull: ſo is he alſo angry: And his anger wyll ceaſe at no tyme agaynſt the wycked. Dylaye not therefore to be conuerted vnto the Lorde: nor put that thyng of from day to daye. For the vengaunce of the lorde commeth ſuddaynely, and in tyme of punyſſhemente he wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroy the: hyther to Sirach.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="remedy">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4762:67"/>
                  <head>¶ The thyrde remedy.</head>
                  <p>BVt an yl coſtome, that thou haſt had in ſyn, letteth the to reforme thy liuing, and to repent, for it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſeen, that men be giuen for the moſt part to ſuch vices, as they haue ben enured with al from their tender yeres, and men do not eaſlye forgette thoſe thynges, wherein they haue of longe tyme ben trayned, As Ciprian ſaith, when doth he lerne to be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in his liuing, which is: and hath benne longe tyme accuſtomed to his deinte diſhes, and his ſumptuos ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers? or when humbleth he him ſelfe to baſe and ſymple apparell, whiche hath gone in his damaſkes, and vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets al the daies of his lyfe? It muſt nedes be that wine drinking with the ſwete taſt therin, as it commonly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, ſhall entiſe a man to it: pryde ſhall puffe hym vp: anger ſett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:67"/> hym on fyre: raueinye vnquiet hym, cruelty pricke him: ambition delight him, pleſure ouerthrowe hym head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe: and ſuch lyke: ſo that it ſemeth to be a thing of muche difficultye, to ouercome this cuſtome, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in ſuche wiſe altered into nature. Yet we muſt attempte it, yf we haue any regarde of our ſoules health. Thou doeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of me: how ſhuld I attempt it. Surely if that thing, which by an yl cuſtome hath preuailed in a man, the ſame thinge be expelled, and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen away by ſome honeſt, and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſe: and if that thing, which thou graffed, thother roote out: what thing is ſo difficile, and harde which by mans wyt, and reaſon may not be atcheaued? Seneca ſaieth: that the minde neuer attempted the thynge, which it brought not to paſſe: A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne redynes of the minde therefore is required: yf a man wil vainquiſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:68"/> and maiſter ſuch a cuſtome that is in a maner vnuincible: rather then con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tention, and laboure: And yet theſe twaine muſt not be lackinge: yf thou wilte plucke vp by the roote ſuche a thing, as ſticketh faſt. Therefore ſet vpon the thing with a good hert, and hauing thy ſpecial truſt in god, that he wyl ayde the, begin it: and vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly thou ſhalte haue good ſucceſſe. It wyl ſeeme a thing very harde: yer thou beginneſt: and in a manner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſyble to be atcheaued: but when thou ſhalte once haue attempted the thing, thou ſhalte perceiue, that that thing, which thou thoughteſt coulde not be brought to paſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out muche difficulty, ſhalbe eaſly wonne. And ſo by experience we try that thing light and eaſy: whiche at fyrſte ſemed won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull harde. If thou ſhalt do thus: that which the poet ſpake by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of Mneſteus, ſhalbe truly
<pb facs="tcp:4762:68"/> verified of the. Succeſſe nouryſheth them. They may do ynoughe, bicauſe they haue opinion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are able. Set but boldelye vpon the thing, as I haue tolde the, truſtynge by Gods aſſyſtaunce to brynge it to paſſe: and then vndoutedly this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and purpoſe to lyue in the feare of god wyll pleaſe the euery day more, &amp; more. Vertue, which in beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty far paſſeth all other thynges, wyll rauiſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. For there is nothing more goodly, or amiable. To be ſhort: thou ſhalte reioyſe very muche, that thou haſt begun to plucke vp, and dryue a way ſuch a naughty cuſtome, whiche hadde taken ſuche place in the. Then thou wylt confeſſe that our ſauiours ſayeng in Mathewe is true, my yoke is pleaſaunt, and my burthen lyght. It is much agreing with this ſame, that Hierom ſaieth in one place: The path of vertu is ſharpe, rugged, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:69"/> vnpleaſant, by reaſon we ar ſo much trained in vice. If this cuſtome were not, then the pathe of vertue ſhulde ſeme to vs ſmoth, veray playne and pleſaunte. He alſo ſpake in an other pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce, bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> truly, and alſo elygantly. If Stilpo the Philoſopher, thoughe he was naturallye dyſpoſed to be a drunkerde, and therunto was verye much enclined: and was giuen natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> yet ſo ouer came, and may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tered by good dyſcyplyne, that naturall incly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation: ſo that he was eſpied to be drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or deſyrous to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhe his pleſure at no tyme: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> maiſt not thou in ſemblable wiſe vanquiſhe by lytle, &amp; lytle a naughe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye cuſtome. A pagain dyd ouercome nature: ſhall not a Chryſtyan then breake the force of cuſtome: ſpecyally yf he earneſtly mynde it, &amp; take hede: and yf he apply him ſelfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge rather, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folowe his appetites, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:69"/> if in conſideracion of mans wekenes he axe, and require gods aſſiſtaunce, and helpe with ardent praier, and by almes dedes, as it were begge gods grace, deſyre the holy ghoſt to be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, which wyll ſtere vp in hym newe motions, and further his ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in vertuous liuing, but let vs go forth with our purpoſe. Let them remember, whiche bycauſe of welth, and riches paſſe for no repentaunce, the threateninges of our ſauyour in Luke: where it is ſayd. O ye rich men wo be to you: bicauſe ye poſſeſſe your comforte: wo be to you: that be fylled bycauſe ye ſhal hunger: wo be to you which laugh: becauſe ye ſhal mourn. Let them remember that thing, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Chryſt ſpake to the ryche man in the Goſpel. Thou foole. This nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> require they thy ſoule of the. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remember alſo that thing, which we recpted in other places concernynge
<pb facs="tcp:4762:70"/> thoſe, whiche were ſodaynelye drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the fludde, and deſtroyed in Soddome with fier, and brymſtone from aboue: concerning alſo the rich men: whom ſaint Iames commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to owle, and mourne for ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeryes as hange ouer theyr heades: And concernynge the ryotoure, dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with veluertes: as Saynt Luke declareth: whiche after his deth was greuouſlye tourmented in hell. Lette vs therefore dryue out, and putte to flyghte this quietnes, and ſecuryte. Let vs not forget God in proſperite. Let vs feare, and dreed the wrathe of the celeſtyall iudge, before whoſe iudgment ſeate we ſhalbe compelled to ſtande bothe lytell, and great, and ſhall there euery man ſpeake in his owne quarel without a man of lawe: &amp; his owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience which is a ſure and certaine witnes of al his ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges and doinges, ſhal accuſe, &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne
<pb facs="tcp:4762:70"/> him, proſperite moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cauſeth a man to aduaunce, and ſet forth him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe. Ryches do make a man ſollem, fearſe, and proude. Therfore let vs alway ſuſpecte fortune, &amp; take heade, leſt this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitorie welth be the cauſe of euerlaſtinge miſerye, and of loſing of the heauenly welth: what wyll ye haue vs to do than? What ye ſhall do: Paule declarethe to you in the epiſtle to the Corinthians: where he ſayeth. This remayneth nowe: that thoſe, which haue wyues, ſo lyue as though they had none: and whiche mourne, as thoughe they mourned not: and which reioyſe, as thoughe they reioyſed not: and which bye, as thoughe they poſſeſſed nought: and which vſe this worlde, as thoughe they vſed it not: for the ſhape of it is not permanent: by which wordes the Apoſtle declareth thus much, that we ſhulde not paſſe much for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4762:71"/> thynges, as wyues, welth, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, aduerſitie, or ſuch lyke: &amp; that our care ſhulde be al together about heauenly thynges: Paule doth not without a good conſyderation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde Timothe to warne rych m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that they be not proude, nor put their hope in vncerteyne ryches, but in the lyuynge god. And the Pſalmiſt. Yf thou haſt ryches at wyl: ſet not thine herte vpon them. In this place we do not plainely condempe riches (for many tymes godly men are rych: but the truſt, and affyaunce, that men haue therin, and the hawtines, and pryde: which procede there vpon: for ryches as we ſayde, make men haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and proude: And therfore it was very wel ſayd in the comedie: bicauſe he was ſet vp, and enryched, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came fearſe and hyghe mynded: let hym than, which poſſeſſeth ryches, &amp; hath good lucke in the worlde, gyue
<pb facs="tcp:4762:71"/> thankes to god, whiche is the geuer, and beware, leſte he be anye thynge proude therof. Let him ſuſpecte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and the flickerynge of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. And alſo lette hym take heade leſt by a certeyne ſecuritie poſſeſſyng his herte, he do forget the lorde god: it is a ſhame for hym, yf he appeare to haue no ſence, nor fealynge of the wrath, &amp; indignation of god againſt ſynne: And if ſluggiſhenes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied euer more with ſlouthfulnes, and lyddernes, take place in hym. Surely it is to be fered, excepte a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take good heade, leſt yf he acquiet, and ſettle hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe in this worldly fely citie and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ynes, he ſhal conceyue falſe ioye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hym ſelfe with hope of a contynuall proſperitie, ſette the feare of god a parte, &amp; by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be ſodeynly caſt away: ſyth that then the laſt day commeth vppon a man euer, when he loketh leaſt for it.
<pb facs="tcp:4762:72"/> Therefore let vs haue euermore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes that thynge, whiche is taught vs in the goſpell, when they ſhall ſaye peace: all thynges are in ſafegarde, then ſodeyne death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vpon them. Let vs not therfore fal on ſtepe: As Paule warneth vs, but awake, and be ſobre. Let vs not ſay: we ſhall haue peace, nor any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl ſhall happen to vs: or lyke as they dyd in Eſay: We haue taken trewſe with deathe: and are at a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt with hell: when the whyppe or plage of god ſhall come: it ſhall not lyght vpon vs. There are very manye teſtimonies of the wrath, and indignation of god agaynſte ſynne, and examples of the punyſhment of the wycked, both in the prophettes, and Apoſtles: wherwith a man may be muche moued, when it chaunceth hym to read them to put awaye this ſecuritie, that we be in, whyles we
<pb facs="tcp:4762:72"/> abounde in ryches: which I purpoſe not to ſpeake of in this place, leſte I ſhulde be to tedious to the gentyll harted readers. For all the reſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs call to remembraunce that thynge, which Moyſes in the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the worlde ſpeketh of mankind which was deſtroyed with water: &amp; of Soddom, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omorra, whiche were turned into aſhes. Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theſe thynges alſo, which we reade both in the prophane hiſtories of great deſtructions of people, and alſo in the olde teſtament of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the people of Iſraell: howe they were often in ſubiection to the Barbarians: bicauſe they neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and broke goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Alſo of the fall, &amp; deſtruction of the Cytye of Ieruſalem. For all theſe thynges are written (as Paule declareth vnto the Corinthyans for our learnynge, which are fallen into
<pb facs="tcp:4762:73"/> the later ende of the worlde. It were to longe at this preſent tyme to ſhew howe greuouſly god hath punyſhed at tymes men for ſinne: and we nead not to ſpeake pertyculerly of euery one. Therfore one example ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce for this purpoſe. Therefore ſyth that the noble Dauyd, kynge of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and one eſpecially beloued of god became not onely in ſecuritie, an adulterer, but alſo added therunto the death of an innocente man, and was therfore greuouſly punyſhed of god: euen after that he had repented and was reſtored into gods fauoure (for he was plaged with the death of his ſonne newely borne, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of his people againſt him, his heuye, and ſorowful chaſyng out of Ieruſalem: with the deſtruction of his concubynes, the fallyng of the people from hym, and laſt of all with the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his cytezens. Such
<pb facs="tcp:4762:73"/> is the wrath and indignacion of god againſt ſinne. Sith (I ſay) that this holy man eſcaped not Goddes ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, and puniſhement for his ſin: and that after that he was reconſiled to god (as it appereth plainely in the boke of kinges) what ſhal become of them (thinkeſt thou) which do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent a whit, but do ſecurely continue in wyckednes, and heape ſyn to ſyn. Let vs nowe therefore moued with thexample of this godly man, ſhake of vs ſluggyſſhenes, and dryue out this drouſye ſecurite, whiche cauſeth vs to acquiet oure ſelues in our ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Let vs liue continuallye in the feare of the lorde God, and ſeeke our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with tremblyng and feare, let vs not ſuffer our ſelues to be ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with any fleſhely luſtes, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but lette vs reſyſt at all tymes with our continuall prayer the temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour the deuyl. And thus much ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4762:74"/> ſuffyce for this parte.</p>
                  <p>Yf any through hope of longer lyfe dyffer the reformacyon of theyr lyfe, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doutles deceiue them ſelues, and do vaynelye loke, and hope for that thinge, which they do moſt earneſtly deſire: And they do ymagyne vayne, and fantaſticall dreames: and what wyl ye more, they wyllingly, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly do periſhe, which I take to be the lewdeſt, &amp; moſt fondeſt thing, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be thought. If theſe thiges, which Hethen Phyloſophers wrote of the ſhortnes, and vncerteyntye of mans lyfe, moue the nothing: As mans life is euen as it were a buble of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And this lyfe is, as a ſhadowe: let that thing moue the, which the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father Iob ſpake. The dayes of mans life are but ſhorte. And. S Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the faithful ſeruant of god. The lyfe of man is as it were, a vapoure appering for a ſhorte tyme, and after
<pb facs="tcp:4762:74"/> euaniſhing away: let this alſo moue the, whiche was ſpoken by hym, that neuer made lye: by our lorde, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chryſte: for he geueth the warninge, and vs all to watche, forſomuche as we knowe neither the day, nor hour. Ye and if theſe wyl not ſerue, let experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moue the: for thou ſitteſt many tymes by thy frendes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng ſicke, without al hope to recouer there helth. Thou arte preſente with them at theyr deathe: Thou heareſt theyr greuous grones, and payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful panges. Thou ſeeſt them brought forth on beers, laide in their graues, and thou thy ſelfe doeſt often tymes burye them. Agayne thou hereſt men in euery place lamenting, and beway<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling their frendes deth. Thou redeſt Epitaphies, verſes wryten vpon dead mens graues: oftentymes thou me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt men in morning weede. &amp;c. which thynges myght put the in mynde as
<pb facs="tcp:4762:75"/> wel of the ſhortnes of lyfe, as alſo of death, whiche at no tyme is farre of: If death of ſtrangers doth not moue vs, we ſhuld be moued with the deth of our familyar freendes, with oure owne proper daungers, that befal to vs all moſte daylye, with our owne ſyckens, wherwith we be not ones or twyſe viſited. And for ſo much as we wey not our wekenes in conſydering the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and plagyng of others we ſhulde remembre it, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it by reſon of our owne aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitye, and ſyckenes, wherewith God plageth vs often times. Which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges yf we conſyder, we ſhall perceyue that we haue very litle cauſe, or none at all to flatter our ſelues with hope of longer lyfe. But in this place ſom man wyll peraduenture ſaye to vs: what? maye we not amende and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme our liuinge ſone ynoughe in our old age? Than I pray you, what
<pb facs="tcp:4762:75"/> ſhulde we do in the meane tyme, but lyue merely, and iocundlye? good ſyr I here you wel: but tel me, I ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre of you by your pacyence: what man is ſure to lyue vntyll that age. Thinkeſt thou to haue occaſion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wylte, to repente: whiche when thou myghteſt commodiouſlye, wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not take it? Nay: thou art far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued: beleue me, thou art deceaued For ſurely god, which of his inexply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cable goodnes wolde that the ſinner ſhulde lyue rather, then dye, when he thinketh tyme, doth call the vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce: and ſtandeth at the doore as S. Iohn ſheweth in the Reuelaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and knocketh. Open the doore therefore, and lette hym in. Here hym which calleth vppon the, and folowe hym, whyther he calleth the. Dyſpiſe not the ryches of the free grace, and goodnes of God leſt thou lay vp for thy ſelfe againſt the day of anger, the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:76"/> wrath, and indignacion of God: As Paul ſaith: vnto the Romains. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not Paul his leſſon vnto the Cor. we beſeche you: brethren, receyue not the grace of god in vaine. I herd the in an acceptable tyme, and am thy fort in the day of ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and helth, by which wordes thus much is decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to vs, that when the tyme of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce is offered, we ſhulde not lette it eſcape vs in any maner wyſe: And that there be not like times, and lyke occaſions giuen, and offered eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry day. Paul hath alſo vnto the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians a ſayeng, that we may very fytly apply to this purpoſe. Whyles we haue tyme, let vs do good workes This was alſo very truly ſayd of the olde doctour: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath promiſed his mercy to the repentaunt: hath not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certeined him of the next morowe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge, whiche dyſſembleth. Thou haſt nede therefore to take hede leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:76"/> by dayeng, and puttyng of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion of thy lyfe, for hope of longer lyfe, thou willingly tempt the Lorde, thy God, whiche of his goodnes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the vnto repentaunce, for this thing we are forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and the expreſſe commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, which is written in Deutero. It chanceth oftentymes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> throughe brawlyng by ſome occaſions giuen, in playeng, and drinkinge a man is ſoddeinelye ſlaine, ſo that there is no tyme then lefte to repentaunce: when otherwyſe we haue tyme, and ſpace grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vs by the ſpecyal grace, and goodnes of God, wherin we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente, and be conuerted vnto health. Let vs not therefore abuſe this exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding gret benefite of our moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and merciful father, which lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it were to haue mercy, and compaſſion vpon vs: Let vs repent, and reforme our liuing by
<pb facs="tcp:4762:77"/> tymes, leaſt we be ſodeinly preuented with the daye of death, and ſeeke for ſpace of repentaunce, and finde it not As the churche ſingeth. For verely he that hath promyſed mercye to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt (As we ſayd once, and muſt eftſones ſaye) aſſured not the ſynner of the next morowe folowyng. But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilte ſaye, that the ſinner may repent them ſone ynoughe, and cry god mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, when he begynneth to ſycken. I graunt it you: but conſyder nowe I beſech the: how many impedimentes and lettes are in that tyme, whiche a man can ſkarſly withſtande, for to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the buſines about making of his laſt wyll, &amp; teſtament: the care for his wife, and children: the payne, &amp; grefe of the ſickenes, and ſuch other, which may appere peraduenture, but lyght matters: how muche thynkeſt thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in that tyme Sathan laboureth: and what wiles, and deceites doth he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:77"/> and imagine to driue a man vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to deſperacyon throughe the multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his ſynnes. For at no tyme ſo much as then the deuyl laboureth to ſet before our eyes, and to call to our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce what euil thing ſoeuer we haue eyther thought, purpoſed, ſaide, or wrought: and ſuch offences: as are otherwiſe greuous of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe he maketh to ſeme a great dele more heynous: And to be ſhort he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by all meanes, that euer he can, to leue vs none hope of forgyuenes, and to driue vs to deſpeire of the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of God by reſon of the multitude, and greatnes of our ſinnes. There is more ouer the vexation, and grefe of conſcyence: There is preſente before our eyes death it ſelf: we bethinke vs of the laſt iudgemente, of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of the lorde, and of hel fyre, who: or what man is able to recken vp euery let, whiche cauſeth a man,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:78"/> that he neyther thynketh, nor yet can thynke of repentaunce in ſuche anguyſſhe. Therefore dyferre not in any wyſe the reformacion of thy lyfe, vntyl the laſt daye: yf thou be wyſe: For it is very perilous, and daunger full ſo to do: that I adde not howe, that ſuch repentaunce, as is conſtrei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by neceſſite, and the feare of hell, and dothe not procede of our owne free wyll, doth but lytell further, and helpe vnto ſaluacion. But this wyll be obiected: that before God there is no tyme of repentance late. I graunt that in verye deade it is ſo: for God wyll no longer remembre the fautes: and offences of a ſinner, then he ſhal repente, and be ſorye in his herte for his iniquyty: And the Prophet ſayth in an other place, that god wyll, that the ſynner rather repente, then dye. But what if ſodaine death ſo opreſſe a man vnwares, that he can not haue
<pb facs="tcp:4762:78"/> ſpace to ſorowe, &amp; bewayle his ſinne, euery man muſt loke for that thinge, which hangeth ouer the heades of al men, and may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indifferentlye to euery one. Cal to remembraunce the ſodeyne death of them, whiche were in the tower Siloa: whiche thynge we reade in Luke: Agayne, what if a man ſhall fall into ſuche a diſeaſe, and ſyckenes, as ſhal take his witte and reaſon cleane from hym? as we ſee dayly by experience. Well yf it ſo happen, as it may well ynough: all hope of repentaunce is gone, and brought to naught, wherunto the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, when he prolonged, and put of fro daye, to daye: the reformation of his lyfe, had moſt reſpecte. Thinke not contrary, but that thyng which fortuneth to others: maye alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to the. For as Publyus ſaythe very wel: That thing, which chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to any one, may chaunce to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:4762:79"/> man, wherefore putte awaye this vayne, and dyceyuable hope of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger lyfe: thinke not to haue occaſion when thou wylt: preſcribe not to thy ſelfe a tyme to repent in, leſt by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge thou increaſe thy foly, or mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as I may call it in differrynge the reformation of thy lyfe. Yf thou be wyſe: repent, whyle thou mayeſt ſinne. For yf thou purpoſe to repent, when thou canſt ſyn no longer: thou ſhalte not ſeame to haue lefte ſynne: but it the. And it is to be feared, leſt when thou myghteſt, thou woldeſte not, that when thou woldeſte thou ſhalte not. The iudgementes of god are vnſearchable in punyſhynge the vyce, and wyckednes of manne. For lyke as of his infinite mercy, and of his excedynge great goodnes he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſpace of repentaunce to ſuch, as are wyllynge, and redy to receyue it: and beareth with ſinners: vntyl they
<pb facs="tcp:4762:79"/> come vnto them ſelues agayne, and be refourmed: ſo verely whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth ſe any man, that he is vtterly loſte, and a chylde of perdityon, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his long ſufferaunce: and iuſtly deſerueth punyſhement: he doth no longer vphold him, bycauſe he run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth headlong into wylful deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but blindeth hym, beynge deſperate, and without hope, &amp; as the ſcripture ſaith, hardeneth his ſtony hert, nor af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwarde loketh for any amendment, or geueth hym an occaſion, as it were to repent, and amende his lyuynge. God doth appoynt for euerye man his day, and ende, beyonde the which a man can not in vyce procede, nor ſurely god wyl prolonge the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin anye longer: which thing myght much moue a man to repente and to refourme his lyuynge, and to ſet aſyde all dilayenge, and to yelde hym ſelfe to the mercy of god offered
<pb facs="tcp:4762:80"/> vnto hym. But nowe let vs go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: bycauſe I haue declared ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently of this parte. Such as do by a certayne truſt, and confydence, that they haue in the popes pardons differ the refourmation, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theyr lyfe, leane vpon a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n, and weake ſtaffe, and ſtay them ſelues by an vnſure holde: none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyſe then they alſo do, whiche worſhyp Barbara of Nicomedeus, and gyue a ſtreyght charge to theyr executors for to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought forth, and buryed in a Franciſcane friers robe: For what mencyon is there made any where in ſcripture of ſuch, eyther in the olde teſtament, and the Prophetes, or in the newe teſtament and the Apoſtles? Or where read we it, that there was any ſuche thynge obſerued in the prymatyue church: or receyued, and approued by a general counſell, as a thynge eyther neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:80"/> or yet profitable vnto ſaluation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Therfore he that bewayleth not his ſines before death, ſhal not be ſaued, thoughe he be bolſtered with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſandes of bulles, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons. Yf thou wylt not then come in to deſpeire of thy ſoules helth, repent the of thy former lyfe, ſettynge ſuche trumperye ware a parte, and when thou ſhalt reknowledge thy ſynnes, be ſory with all thyne herte, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feynedly requyre the mercy of god with prayenge, and wepyng, let thy refuge, and reſortynge for ſuccoure be vnto the merite of Chriſt in a ſure and vndoubted hope, &amp; truſte that god the father wyll be mercyfull to the for Chryſtes ſake, whome for our ſake he delyuered to dye a moſte ſharpe, and ſhamefull death. Thus it ſhall come to paſſe, that god will haue mercy vpon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and forgyue the thy ſynnes, and receyue the into
<pb facs="tcp:4762:81"/> his fauour for Chriſtes ſake. For we haue him an aduocate with the father he prayeth contynually for vs, and reconcileth vs to the father, which is greuouſly offended with our vyce, &amp; naughtynes: he appeaſeth the wrath and indignation of the father: as Ioi declareth in the firſte Catholique E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, Let vs therfore lay away from vs theſe popyſhe pardons, and this ſuperſticious worſhyppyng of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bara, and a Franſciſcane robe to be buryed in. For in theſe thynges no man can conceyue any certeyne hope of ſaluation: Let vs reſorte for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour vnto Chryſt him ſelfe: for he is our mediatour, and aduocate as I ſayde before: he is the very throne of grace: he appeaſed the wrath of god the father for the ſynnes of the world he is the lambe of God, whiche was ordeyned a facrifice for ſynne, frome the beginninge: as we reade in the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:81"/> Reuelacions of S. Iohn: what wyll ye more. He is our rightuouſnes, ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificacion, and redemption: As Paul declareth vnto the Cor. Do not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deferre the reformacyon of thy life for the hope, and truſt which thou putteſt in Pardons, and other ſuche triftles, conſideringe that our lyfe is ſo ſhort, and vncertein: And ſith that death by reaſon of vncerteine chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces hangeth dayly, and hourly, ouer our heades, it may wel ynough come to paſſe that in this preſent moment, when thou leaſt lokeſt for it: it maye creape, and ſteale vpon the: without al dout if thou conſidereſt, how ſhort the tyme of a mans life is: at no tyme it can be very farre of: howe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a thynge is it then to lyue in that ſtate, in the whiche if thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be preuented ſuddeinely by deth, thou wert vtterly caſt away, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned both body, and ſoule. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4762:82"/> for the auoidinge of ſuch daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ieperdy, lyue euer in the fere of God, confeſſe, and acknoweledge thy ſins: reſorte for ſuccour vnto the mercy of god: axe humbli forgiuenes of thy ſins: and truſt aſſuredlye, that by Chriſt thou art ſaued. Repaire of tentimes vnto the miniſter of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion: deſire, that thou maiſt be comforted, and aſſoyled by hym, and that thou mayſt be ſtered to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the promes of the forgyuenes of ſyn: and mayſt be more aſſured and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine of the mercy, and wyl of god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the, come oftentymes vnto the Lordes table: eate of the bodye, which was once offered for the ſinnes of mankinde: eate of it accordingely as he dyd inſtitute it: and drinke alſo of the lordes bloude, which was ſhed for the remiſſion of ſynne: and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſhewinge after this maner the lordes death, and callynge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb facs="tcp:4762:82"/> the benefite, whiche thou haſt receued therby: re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der moſt herty thankes to hym for the ſame: ſynge ſwete ſonges, and laudes before him, with a ioyful, and thankeful hert, as wel at home in thine owne houſe, as alſo in the aſſembles of the faythful. As muche, as euer thou mayſt: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe thy ſelfe from euyll company: and accompanye the vertuous, and godlye: for by them thou maiſt be the better. But receaue ſuch to be thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliers, as thou maiſt refourme, and make better. For it is a great matter and very expedynt to conſider, what maner of felowes thoſe are: whiche are our familiers, and dayly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: for lyke as in accompanienge the naughtye, we be as it were infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a contagyon: ſo verelye by the company of ſuche, as be godlye, and liue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of the lord, our maners are corrected, and amended. With
<pb facs="tcp:4762:83"/> theſe therfore be conuerſant: but with the other neyther make, nor meddle Salomon in the prouerbes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the ſame thynge. And vnto the Cor, S. Paul erneſtlye counſelleth, and exhorteth men to eſchewe the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and company of the wicked: inſomuch that he wold not haue men to eate, and drinke with them. Theſe are his wordes. If any man among you called brother ſhalbe an whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keper, couetous, a worſhypper of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, a railer, a dronkerde, or a raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, neither eate, nor drinke with him And I graunt that there are diuerſe other cauſes, why S. Paul wylleth vs, that we ſhulde eſchewe their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: eyther that we ſeeme not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their vices, or els, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei perceaue that all men for theyr vyce ſake do flee, and abhorre there compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, they might be aſhamed, &amp; repent: But verely the chefeſt cauſe this is,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:83"/> bicauſe he wolde not, that their famy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liars, and companions ſhulde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be infected. For lyke as a lytell leauen dothe cauſe a great heape of doughe to ſoure: ſo verelye thexam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one naughty man corrupteth, and dothe marre a great multytude. And though it is a very herde thyng to leue the company, and familiaryty of ſuche: as thou haſt afore tyme ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued withal long, merely, and pleſant lye: yet verely thou muſt dyligently apply thy ſelfe therunto, and laboure by al meanes, that euer thou canſt, to withdrawe thy ſelfe from theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: Attempt but the thing erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and with a bolde courage: and I dare promiſe the ſuche ſucceſſe in the thynge, as thou woldeſt not thynke. And bicauſe the beginninge, as it is commonly ſaid, is the better parte of the whole: and whoſoeuer begynneth wel, hath (as Horace ſaieth) the halfe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:84"/> of the whole dead, ſet vpon the thing therfore, nor deſpeire in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou conſidereſt with thy ſelfe, howe harde and ful of difficultie the thing it ſelfe is. If it ſhal fortune the to cal to remembrance thoſe feaſtes, which thou haſt kepte with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the rereſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kets, and quaffing, which thou haſt had with them ofte, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes? If it fortune the I ſaye, to fal into any ſuch fonde, and folyſhe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginacion: Againe if thou ſhalt call to remembraunce at any tyme ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy wyll al ſuch good felowes, as thou werte wont to ieſt, and prate withal merely: al ſuch, as kept the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany in playe, and at tauerues: euen then in that ſame very moment cal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to remembraunce the ſhortneſſe of life, death, which is nighe at al tymes the laſt dowme, the iudgement ſeat of the lord, hel and dampnacion? And by this meane thou ſhalte put away, one
<pb facs="tcp:4762:84"/> difficultie with an other. If thou ſhalt reſon with thy ſelfe in this wiſe: my fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes whiche I haue afore nowe, ben merye withall, call, and cry vppon me: deinty ſuppers, bankets, and rereſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, allure me: what ſhal I nowe do? verelye if thou thinke but ſo with thy ſelfe: what ſhal I do? ſtreight way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon weieng, and debatinge the thynge ſhall ouercome the, and thy wylle, and appetyte ſhall without queſtyon be made obedient to reaſon, whiche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and exhorteth menne euer vnto thoſe thinges, which be beſt and moſt profitable for our behofe. Take ſpace therefore, when the deuyll putteth any ſuche thinges in thy mynde, to pouder and wey the thing: and laye awaye all folyſhe niſenes of the mynde: and lette not the appetites bere the ſuffragnitie in any wiſe fal not hedlong, whither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuel wold haue the. What? do thy fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes prouoke the vnto wine drinkig?
<pb facs="tcp:4762:85"/> moderate thou thy ſelfe, &amp; kepe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: bycauſe in a certaine place our ſauiour ſpeketh theſe wordes. Take heed, leſt your hertes be burdened, or ouerladen with meate: Alſo Saynte Paul ſaith: ouercharge not your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with winedrinkinge: for therein is riote: and againe drunkerdes, and rioters ſhall not inheryte the kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god. Alſo S. Peter, be ſobre and awake: alſo Eſay: wo be to ſuch, as do ariſe in the morning to freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and haunte tauernes. And in this place thou muſt remember, that we be more bounden to be obedient, and ſubmit our ſelfe to the auctorytye of the word of god, and of his Apoſtles, then to do a pleaſure, and to gratyfye the deſires of the wicked, and vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, and that we muſt rather obey the good angel, which exhorteth vs, and doth gide vs vnto al good thynges, then the deuyl: whiche intiſeth vs to
<pb facs="tcp:4762:85"/> al kinde of naughtynes: And that we muſt rather withſtande the euyl ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, then repyne agaynſte the good. Wherfore for the pleſaunt company of thy playfelowes, be not cauſe of thyne owne deſtruction, but rather withdrawe thy ſelfe, ſo much, as lieth in the, from them: neither make, nor medle with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Regarde, and eſteme yf thou be wyſe, more thy ſaluacyon, then the ſhorte delectation, that here thou maiſt haue by thy naughtye, &amp; wicked company of thin old co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Se alſo, that thou reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, and diligently wey this thinge, that who ſo doth obſtinately contynue in vyce, doth neyther vnfeynedly repent, nor eyther is, or can be taken for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: for in hym ſurely, whom ſinne pleſeth, trewe fayth can not be, which he lacketh alſo, that ſinneth againſt his owne conſcience, or commytteth any deadly ſyn. Wherfore let vs not
<pb facs="tcp:4762:86"/> be named Chriſtians, when we are farre of, &amp; much differ from the thing it ſelfe: nor yet let vs boſte, and ſette forth our fayth in wordes, but let vs in deade, and vnfeynedly repent, and with all our herte be conuerted vnto the lorde god. Let vs laboure to a mende that thyng, whiche is amyſſe, and by doynge wel, and as we ſhuld and are bounden to do, recompence, ſuch offences, as we haue alredy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: and by thus doyng remoue out of gods ſight the remembraunce of oure former myſdoynges. Let vs referre, and imploye our ſtudies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe endes, that we maye alwaye lyue in the feare of god, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to ryghtuouſnes: let vs in our lyuynge be innocent, vpryght, holye, chaſte, ſobre, and temperate in al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thynges. Let vs profitte the congregation, and helpe the poore membres therof: and to be ſhort, let
<pb facs="tcp:4762:86"/> vs, as Paule exorteth vs, lyue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, and as it becommeth ſuch, as do profeſſe the goſpell of Chryſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge yet for all this our cheafeſt, &amp; ſpecial truſt in the goodnes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of god, &amp; none at al in our ſelues, Let vs praye alſo with out ceaſynge vnto the father by our lorde, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure Ieſus Chryſte, that he wyll vouchſafe to ſende his holy ſpirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, for to lead, guyde, gouerne inſtructe, ſanctifie, raiſe vp, comforth and ſtrengthen vs: like as in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell Chryſte hath promiſed, that the father wyll gyue the holye ghoſte to ſuch, as requyre it of him. And in the meane tyme by geuing place to prau and wicked affections let vs not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte our owne conſcyence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the holy ghoſt, nor baniſhe, and greue hym: but rather (as Paule ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orteth vs) let vs walke in n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>enes of lyfe, and be no ſlaues, nor ſeruauntes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:87"/> to ſinne. Let vs offer oure bodyes a lyuely, pure, and acceptable ſacrifice before god: Let vs crucifie, and kyll the fleſſhe with all the ragious luſtes and pleaſures thereof, and kepe our ſelues pure from the worlde. Let vs be renewed in ſpirite, and put vpon vs the newe man, whiche in ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and true holynes is made lyke vnto the image of god. Let vs be folowers of god, as louynge chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and walke lyke as it becometh the ſeruauntes, and ſaynctes of the lorde, one berynge with an other by loue, and ſtudyenge to preſerue, and maynteyne by the bonde of peace the vnytye of ſpiryte, gentyll, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng one towardes an other. Let vs loue our enemies, praye for ſuche, as curſe vs, do good to ſuch as hate vs, pray for them that vexe, and trouble vs, gyue fode to the hungry, drynke to the thriſtie, money to the pore, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:87"/> neady: Let vs harbour the harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, cloth the naked, viſet the ſycke: ſhewe the way to him, that wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth, inſtructe the ignoraunt, helpe hym, that is in perplexitie, with our good counſell: comforte the comforteleſſe: make agrement amonges them, that are at varyaunce: let vs alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne honoures, forſake vayne glorye, paſſe for no ryches. Finally let vs endeuour to oppreſſe, and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyſhe this naturall enclination to vyce, which is graffed in vs: And let vs not onely beware of this, that our hertes be not burdened at anye tyme with exceſſyue eatynge, or drynking, but alſo prepare oure ſelues ſome tymes by abſtinence, and faſtynge for to pray, and in ſo many, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye aſſaultes of the deuyl, the world and the fleſhe, moſt arde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to require the helpe of god. Neyther let vs be to proude in proſperitie, nor caſte
<pb facs="tcp:4762:88"/> downe in aduerſitie: and what thing ſo euer we do, let vs referre it vnto the glorye of god: not reſpectinge ſo much our owne pryuate profitte, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, as the common profit, &amp; commodity of others. Let vs moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer behaue our ſelues ſo, that we be no cauſe of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to others, but that they may rather by oure example be moued and ſtered vp vnto vertuous and godly behauyour: And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude: let vs pray contynually with out ceaſynge, gyue thankes in all thynges: preace euermore vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye thynges: and ſette the vayne thinges of the world at naught. But thou wylt peraduenture ſay: Theſe thynges are harde, and of much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie. I wyl not denye that thyng: But ſurely they are thynges as well fytte, and agreable to our profeſſion, as alſo neceſſarye vnto ſaluacion. Wherfore in dryuynge out, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſynge
<pb facs="tcp:4762:88"/> this folyſhe nyſenes of the mynd, let vs be very diligent: let vs not pamper our ſelues to much, nor flatter our owne weakenes, nor faile our ſelues wyllingly, ſith that we are not yet deſtitute of the grace of god: Let vs not wetyngely fal into ſynne, but rather ſtrongly reſyſt the deuyll which ſtereth vs, and prouoketh vs thereunto. Let vs not gyue coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ouer at the fyrſte brunte. What thing is not to be thought light, and eaſye, to atteyne that lyfe, whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth withall good thynge, and euerlaſtynge ioye? Paule ſayeth by good ryght. I recken, that the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this preſent lyfe ſhal not be ſo greate, as the glory, which we ſhall haue reueled to vs: which thynge is declared, and proued by this place in ſcripture. For it is written, that the eye hathe not ſene, nor the eare herde: nor the thinges haue not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb facs="tcp:4762:89"/> into the herte of man, which god hathe prepared for them, that loue hym. What a greate thynge is this? Howe ſcarſly can it be not onelye by any mans tongue vtterered, but i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined in the mynde, what a ſtate that is, to be citizen of heauen, heyre of god, partener with Chriſte in his fathers herytage: to poſſeſſe that kingdome, which was before the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion of the worlde prepared for the godly: to beholde euermore the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt felicitie, and greateſt good thing that can be: to ſee, and haue the moſt ſweate contemplacion of gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, to accompnye aungelles: to be in the numbre of the bleſſed ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, in the felowſhyp of the iuſte: to praiſe god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually with himpnes which is the euerlaſtynge ſprynge, &amp; fountayne of al trewe glorye: among aungelles, Patriarches, Prophetes Apoſtles, and all the godly, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4762:89"/> are partakers of the bleſſed, and euer laſtynge lyfe? what? be not all the paines, grefes, and calamites of this lyfe to be thought light, and eaſye, yf thou compare them with the glorye, whiche ſhalbe? Nor hable to deſerue ſuch a rewarde, as is ordeined for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bere thoſe paciently, and take them well in worthe? ſo that we may iuſtly be aſhamed of our niſe delicate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes? what man wolde, I beſeche the wiſſhe to tary here in earth, and not to be diſſolued rather with Paul, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to remembraunce the kingdome of heuen, the immortal lyfe, and ioye, thendles bleſſe, the company of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the felowſhip of al them, which liued here in earth in the ſeruice, and feare of god, and be nowe pertakers of the bleſſed, and euerlaſtyng kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god. Let vs not thinke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that theſe thinges ar difficile, or hard, which Chriſt ſetteth forth to hꝭ
<pb facs="tcp:4762:90"/> diſciples for that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment hereof: ſith that of the contrary wiſe, whoſo doth not kepe gods commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is a thing neceſſary, and nedefull vnto ſaluacion, ſhal not onely be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of that bleſſed lyfe, whiche we ſpake of, but ſhal alſo be caſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to that regyon, and place, where the wycked abide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſhalbe greuouſly tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in hel with ſuch puniſhement, as is ordeined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the deueliſhe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and ſhalbe addict to hel fyer, &amp; endles death, and caſt into that depe darknes, where there is wailing, and gnaſhing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth, and where as they ſhalbe moſt ſharpely, rigorouſly, and euerlaſtingly puniſhed, &amp; tormented: and ſhalbe alſo in the felowſhip, and company of deuyls, and the wycked ſoules without al hope of better: that is to wit, in extreme deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che pricketh, &amp; vexeth a man a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande partes more, then the pein, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:90"/> puniſhment, which he abideth. what man wolde not refraine him ſelfe fro ſin, whiche hath thoſe thinges before his eyes, the feare of hell, endles pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euerlaſting de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, the vnque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheable fire, tormen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is able to tel, the company of deuils, the felowſhip of the vngodly, horror, anguiſhe, continual tremblinge, and quaking, which is ſuch that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be conceaued, muche leſſe deſcribed, &amp; ſet forth in wordes. whom wolde not the day of anger make a ferd? as both the Prophet, and Paul alſo vnto the Ro. calleth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t: the day of puniſhement and afflictio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, the day of miſerye, the day of miſt, and darkenes, the day of cloudes, and tempeſtuous day, when god wyl giue to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to his deſertes? wolde god the remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of thoſe thinges wolde neuer fal out of mens mindes, but that we had them alway ſet before the eyes of
<pb facs="tcp:4762:91"/> our herte. Then men wold be, except I am far deceued, more dyligente in keping the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God. Then men wolde refreyne frome the outwarde acte, and exercyſe iuſtyce. Then wolde they lyue in the feare of God, and accordinge to the rule, and preſcripte of vertue. For ſometymes vertue hath her iuſt rewarde here in this preſente lyfe, lyke as alſo vice, &amp; wickedneſſe haue their deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhement. And that I ſpeake not at this preſent tyme of the teſtimomye, whiche ones mynde beareth againſte him ſelfe, and of the greafe of conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which we haue intreted of in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, let vs now conſider thoſe thinges which are put in daily prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and experience, ſo that they maye not only be ſene, but groped, and felt with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. For to ſpeke of the moſte common, and mooſt frequented vyce amonges men, what miſcheuouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:4762:91"/> I beſeche you, procedeth not nowe a dayes of drunkenes? for of this: as it is noted in the cronicle of the world: palenes of the face: drouſy and ſoore eyes, trembling handes, furious ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, and nightly vnquiet procede. Of this alſo the ſtenche of the breath: the headeache: feblenes of the memorye: and dulnes of wyt come: many times alſo there enſuethe of drunkeneſſe, greuous and very daungerous diſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: as the gout bothe of handes and feete: the fallyng euyll, as both Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians do affirme, and alſo dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience proueth. How oftentymes ſe we alſo whoredome puniſhed in this world, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> french pockes? as alſo we ſe the immoderate pleaſure of the body punyſhed with paulſy, dymnes of the ſyghte, and the dyſſolution of the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowes. What? dothe not ryote alſo bringe many vnto pouerty, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſtate? Is not adultry puniſhed
<pb facs="tcp:4762:92"/> very often by the lawe: and alway is diffamed, and ſlaundered? Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not anger alſo oftentymes hurt here in erth? Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not pryde brough into hatred? Now to what end ſhuld I ſpeke any thing of enuy? for is not it puniſhment ynoughe it ſelfe? doth it not cauſe a man to trete, and chafe him ſelfe? For as Horace ſaith veray wel, the tirauntes of Sicilia did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer inuent a more greuous and ſorer puniſhment, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enuy. Eſteſones: the enuyous man is not a lytel greued in his hert, when other men cheaue and proſpere wel. Doth not the couetous man take great care about the entre ſing of his ſubſtance, &amp; is he not tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled againe, and taketh gret though leſt he ſhal leeſe the ſame? For neither that thig, which he hath, doth ſuffyce hym, nor yet he is at any tyme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſyng that, which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſeth: o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> els he thinketh that it ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:4762:92"/> not laſt: lyke as one man affirmeth. Doeſt thou not nowe manyfeſtly ſee, howe that vyce, and wickedneſſe are puniſhed here in earth? wherwith yf we be nothinge moued, we ſhulde be moued with the punyſhment, whiche the Scripture threateneth to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly in hel, and to be prouoked ther with to refourme, and amende oure lyfe, al procraſtmacion, and dila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eng ſet aparte: yf we take not theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be fables, whiche are mencyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſcripture of thimmortalitie of the godly: and of the endles payne of the wicked. I wyl tel the in few word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> what thyng dyd verye muche moue, and ſtere me to refourme, and amend my lyfe: bicauſe it may alſo peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture geaue occacyon to others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme their liuing. Thus verely I thoughte with my ſelfe: O Riui. What yf it ſhulde happen, that there were none other way euen in this mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:93"/> but preſent death? what I pray the, thynkeſt thou, ſhulde become of the? for doeſt thou perſuade thy ſelfe, that thou arte meete, and redye for death? admytte, that thou doeſt put thine whole truſt, as thou arte boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the goodneſſe, and mercye of God: yet thinkeſt thou, that therefore thou haſt no nede to feare his iuſtice? Howe many thouſandes of Chryſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are adiudged to hell fyre: bothe yonge, and olde men: women, maryed folkes, and vnmaryed: of al ſortes of menne, of euery tyme, and kynrede, whoſe ſynnes haue ben bothe leſſe in nombre, and not ſo gret, as thyne be? Oh fearefull iudgemente, but iuſte. How many Iewes? howe many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppers of Idolles are tormented in hel: which if they had ben conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the faith of Chriſt, as we are through the infinite, and excedynge great mercy, &amp; goodnes of god, wold
<pb facs="tcp:4762:93"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth haue lyued more godly heare in earth, then we do, and had alſo eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped euerlaſting death? Oh execrable vnkindnes: Oh blindnes of our hert what if thou ſhuldeſt here ſuch word, as the prophete Eſay brought vnto good kynge Ezechias: Set thine howſe in order, and make thy ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: for thou muſt dye, and lyue no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: ſayth the lorde: what woldeſte thou do in this caſe. I beſeche the? Then no doubte of it, thou woldeſte wiſhe to haue ſpace to repent, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waile thy ſinnes: Then thou woldeſt crye god mercy with wepyng &amp; ſygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But wherfore doeſt thou not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intende it euery day, and all thy lyfe tyme longe, ſyth that thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt do it in that preſent tyme. When I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered, and thought thus with my ſelfe, I was much awaked &amp; ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp vnto godly lyuynge, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſyn, &amp; in a maner enforced
<pb facs="tcp:4762:94"/> to crye god mercy. This trade maye ſuch men folowe: as thynke it good: where is there any man in the world, which doth not purpoſe to forgyue his enemie before his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th? why doth he not forgyue him euen now aſwel? where is there any man, which wold not be reconc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>led to god with all his hert? why is he not aſwell reconciled euen nowe? Agayne where is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, which is not in mynde to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende, and refourme his lyuynge? Why then doth he not the ſame euen nowe as well? To be ſhorte therfore: what thynge ſo euer thou woldeſt do at the preſent houre of death: do the ſame thyng by the furtheraunce and helpe of god, whiles thou lyueſt here in earth, and art luſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and in good health: that is, to ſpeake perticuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, repent, feare god vnfaynedly, loue hym with all thyne herte, with al thy myght, and power: put thine whole
<pb facs="tcp:4762:94"/> affiaunce, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d truſt in hym: call vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym in aduerſitie, gyue thankes in proſperitie: prayſe, &amp; glorifie him at al tymes: ſyng hympnes, &amp; ſweate ſonges of melodie before him, remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre hym in thy prayers, ſupplycati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and requeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es: commit, and be take thy ſelfe wholy to his wyll, and mercy: Let hi be thine example in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng good to al men: &amp; endeuour to be ſum what like him alſo in loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thine enemies: Take thyne aduerſitie well in worth: be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ryl, and lowlye in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, diligent in thyne offyce, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate aſwel in thyne apparel, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo temperate in eatynge, &amp; drinking: be alſo iuſte in thy dealynge, good to the poore, well aduyled in company: Suffer alſo wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, make loue day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and peace amonge them, that are at debate, and variaunce: be chaſte, baſhefull, ſobre, and honeſt, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryght in al thy doinges. And bicauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4762:95"/> this thynge doth not conſyſt in the to do, thou muſt therefore reſorte vnto God for helpe: thou muſt acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege the weakenes, and vnablenes of man: Thou muſt hartelye, and lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſeke the father to ſtrengthen the with his holy ſpirite, which Chriſte in the Goſpell promyſed that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wolde gyue to ſuch as ſhuld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of him with ardente prayers. If thou ſhalt require than, that thou mayſt haue the holy ghoſt plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aboundantly, &amp; rychly: as Paule ſayth: Powered vpon the by Ieſus Chryſt: by his myght, and his helpe, thoſe thinges, which we could not by natural ſtrength bryng to paſſe, ſhal be ryght eaſelye atcheued. Let this thinge be onely thyne endeuour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to brydle thine affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and beware leſt at any time thou embraſe idlenes or fayle thy ſelfe. For the holy ghoſte doth not iudge them to be worthy of
<pb facs="tcp:4762:95"/> his helpe, which be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dder, and geuen to ydlenes: and ſuch as cantynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues none honeſt thyng to be occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied withall, but ſyt al the day longe with theyr handes claſped together, lyke vagaboundes: But he aydeth workers, &amp; ſuch as put to their owne diligence, and do laboure for to van quiſhe, and ouercome the redines, &amp; inclination vnto vice, which is graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed naturally in vs. Suche I ſaye doth the holy ghoſt helpe, as wraſtle and fyght contynually with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and euyl affections of the mind. Let vs not therfore folow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the carter, which when his cart ſtacke in the tough clay, called vnto god for helpe, but he hym ſelfe ſtode lokynge about hym, and dyd no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thynge. This thyng may alſo feare vs from committinge of euyll, and may alſo ſtere vs vp vnto god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyuynge, bycauſe god is preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:4762:96"/> where, whom thou canſt eſcape in no maner wyſe: and he hath ſet his angel ouer the to kepe, and gouerne the, and to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke, and bere wytneſſe of that thynge, that thou doeſt. Yf thou woldeſt not for any good, that a man ſhulde take the in doyng that thynge, which were not lawefull, nor meete to be done: howe muche more ſhuld the feare and reuerence of god cauſe the to refre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch. Thou feareſt a man wonderfully, bycauſe he knoweth, and is a wytnes of thy naughtynes: doeſt thou then thinke that he which ouerſeeth all thynges, and nothyng doth eſcape, to be fitte, that in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yght thou ſhuldeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelfe to do that thinge, which thou woldeſt be aſhamed to commit in the ſyghte of a man, ſythe that he ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>es iudge the, which is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and marker of all thynges, that thou doeſt? A cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayne Heathen man
<pb facs="tcp:4762:96"/> geueth good counſel, that thou muſt ſo lyue, as though thou werte in the ſyght of all men, and that thy thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king muſt be ſuch, as thoughe there were one, that myght ſe thine inward thought. For it is a great ſtay for a man, when he bethinketh hym that there is one preſent, whiche knoweth his inwarde thinking. A great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinninge is taken awaye, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is a preſent wytnes by: This precepte, and this rewle dyd an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then writer geue: which verely euery Chryſten man ſhulde thynke, that it toucheth him, and is a leſſon for him. If at any tyme therfore thou purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt any vnhoneſt or vnlawful thing, conſyder thus with thy ſelfe, before thou enterpriſeſt ſuch a thyng: what ſhal I do? ſhal I purpoſe that thing in gods ſight, which I wold be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med to do before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Shal I make the holy Aungel mine enemie by this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:97"/> which is ſet to loke ouer, and rewle men: which wolde be looth to cauſe my frende to forſake me. Shal I make the good ſpirite ſory, and the euyll gladde? Did Chriſt redeme me therfore with the ſhedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of his blode, that I ſhulde become the ſeruaunt, &amp; ſlaue of ſinne, and of the deuyll? dyd he make me an inheritoure of the kyngedome of heauen therfore, that I ſhulde leaſe by my negligence the ſame godly, and heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? dyd he delyuer me from ſinne, that I ſhulde wyllyngly, and weatyngly fal into it agayne? Nowe where is that burnynge loue towardes god? Now where is the feare of god? where is the ſhame, that ſhuld be in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? wher is the fayth, and mercy? ſhall I thus recompence the benefites of god? ſhal I render this thanke to Chryſte for the benefitte of my redemption? doth the holy ghoſt ſtere me no more, than
<pb facs="tcp:4762:97"/> thus? Do I come thus vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes table? do I loke thus for the coming of Chriſt? ſhall death take me in this ſtate? ſhal I be ſeen before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of the Lorde in this ſtate? do I ſuffer after this ſorte the wylde affections to beare the ſuffragnite in me? the fleſhe to haue the victory, and vpper hande, and to triumphe ouer me, and ſin to raine in my bodye? Am I a beaſt? haue I not a mans herte? that I thus cowerdly like a daſterde giue place to ſuche mocions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not? do I choſe euer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe when I dayly ſe the better? ſurely if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldeſt conſyder thoſe thynges, and ſuch like, which no man can nombre: thou woldeſt not eaſly committe any vnhoneſt, or vnlawful thinge. What thynge ſoeuer thou doeſt therefore, what thynge ſoeuer thou attempteſt remember, that there is God preſent, as vndoutedlye he is, and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:98"/> and loketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what thinge ſoeuer thou doeſt, or attempteſt: fere, and dreed hym: And for as muche as he is alway preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, let that thing ſum what ſtay the, &amp; kepe the backe from ſin. For as thei ſay he is a witnes: He is a iudge: he beholdeth, what thinge ſo euer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s minde compryſeth. This is a iudge, whom no mannes craftye conueyaunce canne blynde. This thynge ſhall alſo much further, and helpe vnto godlye lyuynge: yf a man call to remembraunce, that by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme he is made the ſon and heyre of god: and that he is alſo made brother of Chryſt, and with hym partener of his Fathers kyngdome, whiche one thynge farre paſſeth, and ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all other. For who wolde not be muche moued with this thynge vnto godlye lyuynge, and wolde not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor by a certeyne natural feare from vyce, whiche remembreth that God
<pb facs="tcp:4762:98"/> is his father? wherfore forget not the benefyt of hym, whiche hath made the by adoption his ſon: Loue hym: wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp hym, feare hym, reuerence hym: and in no maner thynge offende or dyſpleaſe hym: Be obedyente to hys wyll, and pleſure at all tymes, do his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, and folowe it in thy lyuynge expreſly: do not thynke, that onely the pertakynge of his heritage dothe belonge vnto the, but alſo thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitacion, and folowyng of his good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and vertue: So that thoughe thou be not able for to attayne vnto the excellency of that goodnes, which is in god by imitacion, and folowing yet thou mayſt in herte, and wyll ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche nyghe thereunto, and thynke, that it is a great ſhame for the to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from the ſame. If thou com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytteſt that thynge by chaunce, at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tyme, whiche is agaynſt the wyll, and pleſure of the father (lyke as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallye
<pb facs="tcp:4762:99"/> we are all redy to fall) be ſo greued therewith, that thou couldeſt fynde in thyne herte wyllyngly to pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſhe thy ſelfe: and thynke with thy ſelfe that thou haſt deſerued, and art worthy of greuous paynes, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, bycauſe thou haſte offended, and greaued thy father whiche is ſo bountyfull: And ſee, that thou be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer at reſt, vntyll thou ſhalte haue made a recompence with greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, and by true repentance ſhalte haue pacyfied the wrath of thy moſte ientyl, and louinge father: ſo farre of is it that thou muſt wyllyngely treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſe agayne, or permyt thy ſelfe to do or offende in any thynge, that thyne owne conſcyence reclaymeth, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth agaynſt. And verely whoſoeuer remembreth, that he is the ſonne, and heyre of God, the brother of Chryſte, and pertaker with him of his fathers herytage, is not ſo muche terryfyed,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:99"/> with the feare of the laſt iudgement, and of thendles punyſhement in hel, and of the vnquencheable fyer, as he is ſtered with the feare of his fathers offence, and dyſpleaſure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with withdrawe from vyce, and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, nor he is ſo muche induced, throughe hope of the rewarde of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and of the euerlaſtynge ioy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as by a certayne wonderfull, and vnſpekeable loue, that he beareth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his father, to liue innocently to hurte or harme no man, and to do good by thexample of his father to all menne. He that beleueth Saynte Paul, where he ſayeth that our bodye is the temple of the holye Ghoſt, dwel lynge in vs, ſhall eaſlye temper hym ſelfe from doyenge naught, nor ſhall at any tyme pollute hym ſelfe with the beaſtlye luſtes of the fleſſhe. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye who ſo doubteth not, but that he is one of the nomber of thelect and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:100"/> choſen, ceaſeth not after thexample of the Saynctes, to render honour dewe to God, and loue, and charytye, to his neyghboures.</p>
                  <p>But ſome manne wyll peraduenture are, what the cauſe is, that, yf we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to repent, and lyue in the feare of God at any tyme, and after his wyll, and commaundement: or yf we entend to lyue ſoberlye, and chaſtlye: yet we neuer procede, and go on forthe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlye with that thynge, whiche we dyd well, and Godlye purpoſe, vnto the whiche to make a breefe, and ſhort aunſwere: I fynde, that the naturall inclynacion vnto vyce, which is graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed in vs, and is growen in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde partes, and marrowe, is the chefe cauſe hereof: I meane the fleſhe that we beare aboute with vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſpyryte is at contynuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and ſtryfe: as Paul wytneſſeth, We oughte therefore to reſyſte, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:100"/> withſtande at all tymes this ennemy of ours, which allureth vs vnto luſt and fylthy pleaſures: vnto belly chere and gluttony, vnto wanton nyſenes and ryotte, and vnto other vyces, whiche are both fylthy, and vnhoneſt and we ought with Godlye exerciſes trauayles, watchynges, hunger, and faſtyng, to refreyne the violent rage of it: to ſubdue, and tame it with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall ſobernes, and temperaunce. For this is the cauſe, that our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure commaundeth vs to beware, and take hede, leſt our hertes be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with exceſſyue eatynge. And Paul forbyddeth vs to ouercharge our ſelues with wynedrynkynge: He feareth vs alſo from ſurfeytyng, and drunkenes, and commaundeth vs to be ſober, and watche. Agayne conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayer is requiſyt, wherein we muſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the ayde, and helpe of God, without whiche all our endeuour in
<pb facs="tcp:4762:101"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:101"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4762:102"/> refraynynge the fleſſhe, and repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge the vyolente rage of it, is in vaine. But now, when we haue thus refrayned the mocions of the fleſſhe: there remayne yet two ſore ennemies the worlde, and the deuyl, with which we muſt fyght contynuallye without ceaſſyng: bycauſe they ſuffer vs not to perſyſt, and contynue in a Godlye purpoſe, to lyue vertuouſlye. For the worlde moueth vs vnto ambycion, pryde, anger, hatred, enuye, malyce, impacience, backebytynge, and vnto other ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of wickedneſſe, which no man is hable to nomber. It offereth many occaſyons, and cauſes, &amp; with examples it corrupteth vs. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> uyll ſtereth vs to neglecte the worde of God, to myſtruſt, and dyſpeire of the mercy of God, to conceyue a falſe perſuaſyon of oure ſelues, to perſyſt obſtynatly in vyce, to ſpeake blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye agaynſte God, to impugne his
<pb facs="tcp:4762:102"/> knowen truth, he prouoketh vs vnto hypocryſye, ſuperſtityon, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, and vnto infinite, and vnnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable kyndes of wyckedneſſe? thou axeſt, what were to be done in this poynte? Valiauntly we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſt, and withſtand our enemies, and lay away from vs al folyſheniſenes: we muſt with our moſt erneſt prayer axe, and craue the ayde, and helpe of god, &amp; thus if we put our affiaunce, and ſtedfaſt truſt therin, we neade in no wyſe to deſpeyre of the vyctorye. Let vs therfore heare that thynge, whiche S. Paul ſayth vnto the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inthians. This remayneth ſayth he my brethren, that ye be ſtronge, and ſtedfaſt in the lord, and in the might of his power: put vpon you the whol armoure of god, that ye may be able to ſtande agaynſt the aſſaultes of the deuyll. For our ſtryfe is not againſt fleſhe, and bloude, but agaynſte ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:103"/> and poteſtates, agaynſt lordes of the worlde, the princes of hel: and agaynſt theyr gyles, and deceytes. And ſpeking afterwarde by name of that ſame armoure he commaundeth them to ſtande ſtrongly vnder pight with trueth, hauynge for theyr breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, iuſtyce, for theyr bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lar, fayth: where with ye may be able ſayth he, to extinguyſhe, and quench al the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dartes of the deuyll. Moreouer he commaundethe them to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them the Helmette of ſaluacion, the ſwearde of the holye Ghoſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the woorde of God: and he wylleth them neuer to ceaſe of from prayenge at any tyme. I haue nowe ſhewed the an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmoure, or as Paule termeth it, a protection, to defend vs agaynſt our fearſe enemie the deuyl, which ſurely letteth no daye eſcape, yea none houre, or momente of the houre, wherein he doth not ſet vpon
<pb facs="tcp:4762:103"/> vs, to ouerthrowe vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For as ſaynt Peter ſayeth: He walkethe aboute continuallye lyke a rorynge Lyon, ſeakynge whom to deuoure: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beynge decked, and armed with the armoure of Paule: Lette vs manfully reſiſte the proude ſpirite: And S. Iames aſſureth vs, that ſo we ſhall vanquiſhe him, and put him to flyght: Let vs reſorte vnto god for ſuccoure continually, and praye, and ſeake of hym, that he wyll not ſuffre vs to be led into temptacion, but for Chriſtes ſake delyuer vs from that tyraunte, which is an euerlaſtyng e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie of man kynde. And let vs take good heede before all other thynges, that we wetingly do not fal into that ſinne, whereunto he moueth vs, nor into wylfull deſtruction. Let vs not cheriſhe, and vpholde our owne fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe delycate niſenes, but rather ſtoutly withſtande Satan, &amp; in our
<pb facs="tcp:4762:104"/> ſupplicacions requyre of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal god, the father of our lord Ieſus Chriſt: that in ſuche infirmitie, and weakenes he wyl helpe, and ſupport vs. And for ſo much as the deuyl ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſetteth on vs openly, nor denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth warre before, but ſtealeth vpon vs, and lyke a wylye fox oftentymes ſpeaketh fayre to vs for to compaſſe, and deceyue vs, and laugheth vpon vs to endomage, and hurte vs, and allureth vs vnto the vtter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſowles, we muſt warely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe his ſnares, which he hath laid for vs. Let vs not gyue occaſion, nor offer a fitte, and conuenient tyme to hym for to aſſaulte, and oppreſſe vs vnwares. Cyprian ſayth that a man may the better beware, when he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Therfore lette vs ſhake of vs ſlouthfullnes, and ſet a part al ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: and as it is commonly ſaid, let vs feare the Scorpion vnderneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:4762:104"/> ſtone, let vs not be without care in ſecuritie, as though all were well, and in ſafegarde. No man is ſooner vndoone, than he, whiche is without feare, as an Heathen man wryteth, &amp; this ſecuritie is the begynnyng of al myſcheafe, and calamitie. Yf thou haſte therfore ones tryumphed ouer thine enemie, &amp; vanquiſhed hym, do not ſtreyght way thinke, as thoughe al dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger were paſt, that thou ſhalt lyue continually in peace: thou muſt ſtande ſtyl in the front of the batayle redy to fyght, as Ciprian exortethe: Thou muſte in this worlde do none other thynge, but fyght contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ally with the Deuyll, and keape of thee his dartes, and weapons with the buclarre of fayth, and the ſwerde of gods worde. We muſt fyght, ſayth he with auarice, with vnchaſtitie, with anger, &amp; ambition: we muſte wraſtle continually with carnall vyces, and
<pb facs="tcp:4762:105"/> the temptacions of the worlde: for our ſoule, conſiderynge that it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the whole armye of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, is ſcarſly able to ſtande againſt ſuch a violent aſſault. For if auarice be ſupplanted, luſt putteth oute the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ade. If luſt be vanquyſhed, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuccedeth: yf ambicion be ſette at naught, anger is placed for it: &amp; thus pride puffeth vp the hert of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wine drinkynge allureth, enuye bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth concorde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elowſye dyſſolueth frendeſhyp, and amitie. And lyke as we muſt not be proude, beynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queroures, ſo when we are conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted we muſte not ſtreyght waye deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyre, and laye awaye frome vs our weapon. What muſt we then do? ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely we muſt then fyght more fearſly then euer we dyd before, for to remeue and take awaye the former ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſhame: and with valiaunte courage to quitte oure ſelues of the
<pb facs="tcp:4762:105"/> foyle receyued at the handes of oure enemie: like as a certayne noble man dyd, which is artificially peynted, &amp; ſet forth in his coloures by an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent poet: whoſe wordes theſe be of the ſame. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was beaten downe vnto the grounde with great ſtones which his enemies caſte downe vpon him, he was not therfore vanquiſhed and put to flyght, but was then more fearſe, then euer was he before. For anger pricked hym forwarde: and ſhame, and his knowen proweſſe did ſtere, and inſence him: albeit we muſt fight with our enemie, hauyng more affiaunce in god, then in oure owne ſtrength. Now thou perceyueſt, what the cauſe is, why if we purpoſe to liue godly at any tyme, we continue not therein. A certayne enclination vnto ſinne, which is naturally graffed in vs, is chefely the cauſe: nexte of all, the worlde, which miniſtreth ſundry
<pb facs="tcp:4762:106"/> occaſions vnto al kynd of vyce: Laſt of all the deuyll whiche caſteth with him ſelfe contynually how to deſtroy vs, nor ceaſeth at any tyme to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe vs eyther openly, or priuilye. God, and the father of oure Lorde, and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt encourage and ſtrengethen vs in this daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and contynual conflycte, with ſo many enemies, and ſupporte vs with his helpe, which are vnable of our ſelues to reſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with his holy ſpirite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme &amp; eſtabliſhe our hertes, that we may both ouercome, and brynge lowe theſe fleſhely moci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor be yet ouercomen, &amp; brought downe by the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions of the ſame and that we may ſuppreſſe our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall concupiſſence, &amp; reſiſt the world, which geueth diuers, and ſundry oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſious vnto ſinne: and that we may alſo withſtand the deuyl which tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs by al meanes poſſyble, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenteth
<pb facs="tcp:4762:106"/> al maner of giles, and waies how to deſtroy vs: and that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſeruile, and bonde feare, which the lawe bryngeth, may reuoke, and withdr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vice by a certayne ſeruyle dreed, and feare of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god, and of euerlaſtinge tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and paine, being fered with the wrathe, and iudgement of God, and the terror of hell, but rather a greate dele the liberal, &amp; honeſt feare, which natural children haue to breake, and tranſgreſſe the commaundement of their dereſt father: whiche feare true faith verely doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre, may moue vs withal honeſt, godli, and reuerent behauior at no tyme to do, or atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte that thing, wherwith ſuch a benigne and bountiful father may be greued and offended: and that this thynge may moue vs for to do well: of oure owne free wyll, and to flee, and abhor vyce, and to do our bounden deutye
<pb facs="tcp:4762:107"/> euen of a loue, ſo that yf we haue at vnwares ſuffered our ſelues to treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, or offend any thing by frailtie, that thynge may ſo greue, and vexe our conſcyence, that we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lde verye gladlye, and willinglye puniſſhe our<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, and thynke, that we wolde be rather dead, than alyue: bycauſe we haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded our father, whiche is ſo merciful, and bountious. This thing alſo the euerlaſtyng god graunte for his ſons ſake our lorde, and ſauiour Ieſus Chryſt, that conſyderynge the ſhortnes of our lyfe, &amp; the vncerteine hour of death, we difer in no wiſe the amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our life, but returne ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther vnto ſaluacyon, acknoweledge our ſins, and repent, vnfeinedly, and pacify with a ſoroful, &amp; contrite herte the wrath of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuenly father, &amp; knoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king our breſtes with the Publicane in the goſpel, require humbli the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of god, &amp; that we wyl, and laboure
<pb facs="tcp:4762:107"/> for to attaine ſuch thinges onely, as are acceptable in gods ſight, &amp; make a greter mendes for our offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, than thoffence it ſelfe is, and by good workes, and almes deedes recompence our fautes, and putting thus our affiaunce, and truſte in the goodnes, and helpe of God, that we may liue in the ſeruice, &amp; feare of god innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, as Chriſten men ſhuld do, chaſtly, ſoberly, and temperatly: For the profytte of the congregacyon of Chriſt, and of mans lyfe, agreably to the profeſſyon of Chryſten men, and herein may thus ſtyll continewe, and perſyſt vnto the laſt daye.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were the thynges, whiche I purpoſed to ſhewe of the foly of men bicauſe they difer, and put of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to daye the reformation of their lyfe, our purpoſe dyd conſtreyne vs to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, &amp; bryng forth certeyne thinges, whiche lyke as they wyll be pleſaunt
<pb facs="tcp:4762:108"/> and well accepted of the godlye, that loue, and feare god, ſo wyll they be to thother bitter, and vnpleſant, whiche wolde be taken for Chriſtians, whan they are none in very deed. We ſpake manye thynges euerye where of the ſhortnes of lyfe, &amp; of the vncerteintie of deth, which is euery hour at hand, by reſon of vncerteine chaunces, and oppreſſeth vs oftentymes, whan we leaſt weene. But notwithſtandynge godly men do wyſhe for it, and when it pleaſeth God, wyllyngelye, and deſyrouſlye enbraſeth it. The vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly do not ſo: they feare it wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully. We ſpake alſo of the reſurrection of the deade, of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the lorde, of the laſt dowme, when al men ſhal be called to gyue an accomptes and reckening of their former lyfe, which day wil be to the wicked very terrible but much loked for, &amp; wyſhed of the godly. For then doth theyr redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:4762:108"/> approche: then the tyme of refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinge, as we reade in thactes, is at hande, and as Tertullian ſayth, the day of Chriſten exultacion draweth nyghe. We declared alſo, what peine and punyſhement was ordeyned for the wycked after this bodely death, and what reward and pleaſure was repoſed in Chriſt for the godly. For then the godly ſhal come vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhal there lyue in the greateſt ioye, that can be. Howe great ioye, and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie muſt it neades be, for to behold gods countenaunce euer more, to be gladdened with the continuall, and moſte comfortable contemplation of gods vyſage, whom nowe we ſe but coueredly, as Paule ſayth? How great felicitie muſt it neades be, to ſe hym, as he is of him ſelfe, to abound with all good thynges, to enioy ſuch greate ioyes, and ſo manye in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, as no man is able to conceyue,
<pb facs="tcp:4762:109"/> muche leſſe to vtter, and expreſſe in wordes. But the deuelyſhe ſhall be caſt headlong into hell pit, and there ſhalbe tormented with endles peyne. Neyther ſuch is the vtteraunce, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence of any man, that he can be able to deſcribe, &amp; ſet forth in wordes, nor ſuch is the ſharpenes of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wyt, that he can conceyue but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the leaſt parte of thoſe peynes, which the wicked ſhal abyde, &amp; ſuffre in hell: which are condempned by the iuſt iudgement of god, vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng fyre. Finally we ſpake of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thynges mo, whiche wylbe to the Godlye verye pleaſaunte, and comfortable, but otherwyſe to the wycked, and deuelyſhe. As of gods wrath agaynſt ſinne, of dryuyng out of our mindes ſecuritie in welth, and proſperitie, of repentaunce, amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reformation of our liuing, of the continual wraſtlynge, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle;
<pb facs="tcp:4762:109"/> that we haue with our extreme enemies the world, the fleſhe, and the deuyll, and other ſuch lyke, which it is nedeles now to reherſe: Theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges are bitter, and vnpleſaunte, but as I truſt, healthfu. For Phiſitians cure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly greuous, &amp; ſore diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with ſharpe medicines, as <hi>Curei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſheweth. Alſo <hi>Cicero</hi> in an Epiſtle vnto Octauian ſaith, that no ſalues which ar laid vnto ſores, do ſo much grene the pacient, as do thoſe, which are helthful. The euerlaſtynge god graunt this, the father of our lord, &amp; redemer Ieſus Chriſt, that in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o wycked, and corrupte world, this our laboure may kepe the godly in their offyce, and therin confirme, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if at leſt wiſe any wil reade this litle treatiſe, haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a zele: to the wycked alſo, that it maye miniſtre ſome occaſion to retourne, and repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And that the ſalue, which is taken, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4762:110"/> layde to the ſycke, and well nere deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate for healthes ſake, maye haue power to eaſe them, and worke theyr ſaluacyon. This thynge graunt he without whoſe helpe al our endeuor, and ſtudy is voyde and in vayne, the almightye, and euerlaſtynge God, to whom be al prayſe, honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, nowe and euer. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke .xii Chap.</bibl>
               <q>¶ Be in a redines therfore, bycauſe at what houre ye leaſte weene, the ſonne of man wyll come.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> IMPRYNTED AT LONDON IN FLETE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrete at the ſigne of the George nexte to Saynte Dunſtones Churche by Wylly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Powell.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:4762:110"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
